<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nature and principles of love, as the end of the commandment declared in some of the last sermons of Mr. Joseph Caryl ; with an epistle prefixed by John Owen ...</title>
            <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C781</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4133</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12375925</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12375925</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60602</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35541)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60602)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 933:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nature and principles of love, as the end of the commandment declared in some of the last sermons of Mr. Joseph Caryl ; with an epistle prefixed by John Owen ...</title>
                  <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 125, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by John Hancock, senior and junior ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Love --  Religious aspects --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60602:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60602:1"/>
            <p> THE NATURE AND PRINCIPLES OF LOVE, As the END of the Commandment.</p>
            <p>Declared in ſome of the laſt <hi>Sermons</hi> OF M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Joſeph Caryl: With an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> prefixed by John Owen, D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>John Hancock, Senior</hi> and <hi>Junior,</hi> at the Sign of the Three Bibles in <hi>Popes-head-Alley</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1673.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60602:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60602:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Sermons were preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of them a little while before his Entrance into Reſt. I cannot learn that the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of them were <hi>extraordinary,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:60602:3"/> or that he had any deſign in them be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yond that which accompanied the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinary courſe of his Miniſtry; muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſs a purpoſe to publiſh them, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conceiving them either more uſeful or more needful, or more laboured than the reſt of his conſtant and frequent Exerciſes in the ſame kind. Neither did he leave any ſuch <hi>Copy</hi> of them as might be helpful towards ſuch an end. But they were taken from his mouth by the diligence of a Dexterous Hand, who at firſt deſigned nothing but his own uſe and edification by them; untill obſerving how ſoon after the preaching of them, God was pleaſed to call him off from his Painful Labour in his Vineyard, and ſo to cut ſhort all expectations of farther adminiſtrations of Truth and Grace, by the Truſt and Diſpenſation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto him; he reſolved to make them publick, for the good and benefits of others. And as herein
<pb facs="tcp:60602:3"/> he followed his own Inclination and Judgement; So if any thing be found in theſe Diſcourſes as to Phraſe of Speech, or manner of Expreſſion, not anſwering that Accuracy, which this Author was known to have uſed in all his Writings publiſhed by himſelf; he alone muſt bear the blame of it, from them who think ſuch defects blame worthy. Theſe things I could not but acquaint the <hi>Reader</hi> withal, that he may look for no more in theſe Sermons, but what he might have found in the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> Miniſtry of the Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. But yet I muſt ſay, upon their peruſal, that take them under the Circumſtances mentioned, they give no ill or diſadvantageous Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Ordinary Labours and Endeavours of this Eminent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel. Thus did Mr. <hi>Caryl</hi> uſe to preach, ſometimes <hi>twice,</hi> ſometimes <hi>thrice</hi> in the Week, alwayes ſhewing himſelf a
<pb facs="tcp:60602:4"/> Workman that needed not to be aſhamed. And if I miſtake not; whoever ſhall conſider theſe Sermons with Sobriety, Candour and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as part of his Conſtant La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, will readily acknowledge, what rich and excellent Talents he was entruſted with, and how the great Reputation which his Miniſtry had for ſo many years in the Church of God, was no way undeſerved. For my Acceſſion to this Work in a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatory Diſcourſe, it aroſe meerly from the importunity of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſher and Bookſeller, as they both well know, and will acknowledge; wherein I ſee nothing my ſelf of uſe or advantage, but only that I may tender ſatisfaction to the Reader, that he is not Impoſed upon by any Spurious Offspring fathered on ſo great and worthy a Name. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what alſo I was inclined unto a Compliance with their deſires, that I might make uſe of this Advantage
<pb facs="tcp:60602:4"/> a little, to declare, How I have been Treated by others in things of this Nature. Not long ſince came forth ſome Sermons of a Worthy Perſon now alſo at reſt with God, with an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> prefixed unto them, whereunto ſome <hi>Letters of my Name</hi> were ſubſcribed. This occaſioned a Perſon at that time (for I hope he is ſince grown wiſer) deſigning a Reputation in Buffoonry, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh a Reviling Letter <hi>to</hi> me, or againſt me about that Epiſtle, which I wrote no more than he did him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; nor do believe had known to this day, either of Book or Epiſtle, had I not heard of it from him, and ſome other like minded with him. But he ſeemed to have had a deſign, towards whoſe accompliſhments, that practice was judged neceſſary. Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo, the Importunate Solicitations of a <hi>Bookſeller</hi> prevailed with me to write a ſhort <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Concordance</hi> which he had
<pb facs="tcp:60602:5"/> newly publiſhed; and no ſooner had I done it, but in the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of Books Printed the laſt <hi>Term,</hi> the <hi>Concordance</hi> it ſelf is Repreſented as Compleated, Finiſhed, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by me, who never added nor altered one word or ſyllable to it, nor in it. And having now thus far diverted from the preſent Occaſion, I ſhall crave leave of the Reader, to proceed a little further in an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of one or two other Diſingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities of the like kind, taken out from a numberleſs heap of impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Untruths and Calumnies. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe many falſe and fierce Accuſations which one of Late hath ſtuffed his Scandalous Writings with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, there is none which ſeems more Accommodated to his purpoſe, than my Compoſing or Subſcribing a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per publiſhed about the Year 1658. containing the propoſals and deſires of the Subſcribers with reſpect to publick affairs. This Paper the man
<pb facs="tcp:60602:5"/> lighting on, ſuppoſing he had obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a mighty Advantage by finding the Letters of my Name, or my Name it ſelf ſet unto it, he ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, and challengeth, and Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth in ſomewhat a peculiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, though that be difficult for him to do. Yet all this while I have juſt reaſon to believe, that he knew the Paper was none of mine, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I had no concernment in it; for as the things contained in it were directly contrary to my known and avowed Principles both then and now: So it was alwayes notoriouſly known, that it was another Perſon who without any <hi>forgery</hi> could uſe that Name, whoſe ſubſcription it was, as will be acknowledged by the ſurvivors of the Subſcribers. I confeſs when the Paper it ſelf was firſt brought to me (as it was by a Learned Perſon now in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Oxford)</hi> I expreſſed ſome Indignation againſt it; as ſuppoſing
<pb facs="tcp:60602:6"/> that I had been then dealt withal, as I have been of late, by putting my Name unto what I was no way concerned in. But quickly hearing that he who had ſubſcribed that Name, had right ſo to do; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own as well as mine, (though I find ſince alſo that there was in it, ſome intention to deceive) I gave neither him nor my ſelf any trouble about it. In like manner the ſame Author affirms, that ſome Perſons at their return from their Conqueſt at <hi>Ireland,</hi> were made Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors at <hi>Oxford</hi> by <hi>J. O.</hi> whereas one of the Perſons mentioned, never came out of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and the other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came to <hi>Oxford</hi> after his return; but had indeed with another perſon that Ceremony of Reſpect ſhewed unto him ſometime before in that Univerſity, not by <hi>J. O.</hi> but by <hi>E. R.</hi> now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Norwich.</hi> But I crave the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders pardon for this diverſion eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, having turned aſide into a
<pb facs="tcp:60602:6"/> dirty Rode, wherein there is not any thing of Chriſtian Sobriety, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Ingenuity from firſt to laſt to be found. Yet what Violences have been offered unto the Sacred Truths of the Goſpel in Important Articles of Faith, and other things ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to Chriſtian Religion, will in another way be called to an Account, as ſome of them have been already; whereunto a Return may be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of raging and beſtial Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and no other. Here I ſhall not farther Indiſpoſe the Reader unto the ſerious peruſal and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the enſuing Spiritual Diſcourſes, wherein there is more Worth and Uſe, more that will turn unto a Refreſhing Account at the laſt day, than in a thouſand Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Conteſts managed with Pride and Paſſion, what ever pretences they may be gilded withal.</p>
            <p>That he who miniſtred this ſeed to the Sower, would multiply the
<pb facs="tcp:60602:7"/> ſeed ſown, and give it an Encreaſe in the fruits of Righteouſneſs among them that through his Providence ſhall be made partakers of it, is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Servant in the Work of the Goſpel, John Owen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60602:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 TIM. 1. 5.</bibl>
               <q>Now the end of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is Charity, out of a pure heart, and of a good Conſcience, and of Faith unfeigned.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE holy Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as appears in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Chapter and Epiſtle, finds ſome at <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> who troubled the Church with needleſs, and with fruitleſs Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and therefore if you conſult the third and fourth Verſes of this Chapter, you will find he beſought <hi>Timothy</hi> to abide at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> when he went into <hi>Macedonia,</hi> that he might charge ſome, that they teach
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60602:8"/> no other Doctrine <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Teach Doctrines contrary to what he had taught; or Doctrines contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the General Tenour of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. Such Teachers he calls <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed,</hi> Gal. 1. 8.</p>
            <p>He would have him warn them at the fourth Verſe, <hi>Not to give heed to Fables, and endleſs Genealogies, which miniſter queſtions, rather than godly edifying, which is in Faith. Timothy</hi> was beſought by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to give this charge to, and concerning the Teachers at <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe thoſe Fabuliſts and Genealogiſts, were great pretenders to the Law, therefore the Apotle tells them, That the Law leads to the embracing of one another in love; not to the imbroyling of one another in needleſs queſtions, or in the venting of them: and this he ſpeaks in the Verſe now Read, <hi>The end of the Commandment is Charity out of a pure heart, and of a good Conſcience, and of Faith unfained.</hi> In
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60602:8"/> which words we have two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, An Aſſertion laid down.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We have a limitation to the Aſſertion.</p>
            <p>The Aſſertion is laid down in the beginning of the Verſe, <hi>The end of the Commandment is Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Aſſertion is limited in the cloſe of the Verſe, 'Tis <hi>Charity,</hi> not Charity at large, but Charity thus qualified, or thus circumſtantiated—'Tis <hi>Charity out of a pure heart, and of a good Conſcience, and of Faith unfeigned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt explicate the Aſſertion, and then ſhew its Connexion with the limitation, and give at the preſent one General Point of Doctrine from the whole Verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The end of the Commandment is Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the explication of this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, I muſt ſhew three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What's meant here by the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:60602:9"/> 2. What's meant by the <hi>end</hi> of the Commandment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What that <hi>Charity</hi> in ſpecial is, which is the end of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And when I have briefly done theſe three things, we ſhall come to a Point.</p>
            <p>The end of the <hi>Commandment</hi> is Charity, but what's this <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word which we here tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate Commandment, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not the ordinary word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies a <hi>Commandment;</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and the word properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, as Criticks tell us, A charge given by Judges or Superiours, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſomewhat to be done, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born; and thus 'tis uſed in <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 28. where the High Prieſts tell the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Did not we ſtraitly command you, that you ſhould not teach in this Name?</hi> Did not we ſtraitly <hi>Command</hi> you? The Greek there is an Hebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, in which St. <hi>Luke</hi> doth there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the minds of the Scribes and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60602:9"/> Phariſees, <hi>Did not we ſtraitly</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Did not we command you with a Command? which we very well render according to the ſenſe of the Idiom, Did not we <hi>ſtrictly command you?</hi> Or as Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> renders it, Did not we command you again and again? And in the very ſame ſenſe doth the Apoſtle uſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the 18th Verſe of the firſt of <hi>Timothy:</hi> This <hi>charge I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi> unto thee. Why now if we ſhould take the word Commandment in this ſtrict ſenſe, it may have a ſpecial reference to the third and fourth Verſes going before the Text, whereas I toucht before, St. <hi>Paul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought <hi>Timothy</hi> to charge ſome, that they teach no other Doctrine, To <hi>charge</hi> them, or to Command them. 'Tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is the root of the word which we render Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment. I charge thee to lay this Commandment upon them. So we may well render it, I command
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60602:10"/> they teach no other Doctrine. As if he had ſaid, the end why I beſought thee to give that charge, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, was to promote charity: whereas thoſe other Doctrines, did but breed queſtions, and thoſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions breed Contentions among the Churches, and among the Brethren, <hi>the End of the Commandment,</hi> the reaſon why I gave them that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, was to maintain love among Brethren.</p>
            <p>Yea for as much as the Apoſtle at the 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> ſpeaks of thoſe who deſire to be Teachers of the Law, and in the 8. and 9. <hi>verſes,</hi> proceeds to ſpeak of the nature and uſe of the Law, I conceive the Word <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> may be extended to the whole Law of God, or to the whole Revelation, or the mind of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning things to be done, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born by us. And ſo here is a figure, here's a change of number, the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular is put for the plural, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi> for <hi>Commandments,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60602:10"/> and indeed, as the Doctrine of Grace is nothing elſe but a Collection of promiſes, ſo the Law is nothing elſe, but a Collection of precepts, and in this ſenſe ſaith Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> here, by the word <hi>Commandment,</hi> we may take in all the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God. Not only thoſe that are expreſt in the Decalogue, but thoſe which are ſcattered quite through the Holy Scriptures. The end of the Commandment, or of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, the whole Revealed will of God, concerning the <hi>Agenda,</hi> or things to be done, It is charity, or it is Love; and ſo much for the firſt thing, what we are to underſtand by the Commandment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what is the <hi>end</hi> of the Commandment, the <hi>end</hi> of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment is <hi>charity.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>end,</hi> may be taken in a threefold notion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>end,</hi> it notes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, and Period of a thing, the concluſion of all things; ſo the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in his 1 Epiſt. 4. 7. <hi>The</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60602:11"/> 
               <hi>end of all things is at hand,</hi> and it's well for us to Remember that, If the end of all things were at hand in the Apoſtles time, how near is the end now, the end, the Period of all this viſible world, it is at hand, <hi>Be ye therefore watchful, and ſober.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>End,</hi> notes as much as the Aim, deſign, plot, ſcope of any Action, what it is that we drive at; and in that ſenſe 'tis well ſaid, <hi>That the deſire of the end is endleſs,</hi> that is, men <note place="margin">Appetitus finis eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitus.</note> will never end their deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings till they have attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their deſired end, namely, that which is the ſcope, and Aim, which they have ſet up to themſelves in any undertaking: the end of a thing is the Aim, or the ſcope of it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, End is taken in this notion, It notes the accompliſhment, or the fulfilling and Compleating of a thing, and in that ſenſe it is uſed in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 4. <hi>Chriſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>the Apoſtle,) is the end of the Law for</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60602:11"/> 
               <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> The end of the Law, he hath brought the Law to its end—what end? why to its ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, to its fulfilling, ſo that we are not to ſeek for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by the Law for our Juſtification, for Chriſt hath made an end of the Law, or accompliſhed the Law, as to that point, for righteouſneſs, Chriſt hath fulfilled the Law, both in doing the precepts of it, and he hath fulfilled the Law by enduring the penalty of it, and ſo he is the end of the Law, the fulfilling end of the Law; It hath no more to require than that we obey the precept, or endure the penalty of it, and both theſe Chriſt hath fully done, and ſo he hath fulfilled the whole Law, and Indeed, Chriſt having done ſo in his own perſon, having been the end of the Law in his obedience, both active and paſſive, I may ſay, He is the <hi>Aboliſhing</hi> end of the Law, he hath taken it away as to that uſe, for Juſtification by our own works, the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60602:12"/> Law is quite out of doors, as to that point, Chriſt is the end of the Law for righteouſneſs, and no more are we to ſeek for righteouſneſs by the Law.</p>
            <p>Why now in the text, the word <hi>end,</hi> when 'tis ſaid that the <hi>end of the</hi> Commandment is charity, the word <hi>(end)</hi> is to be taken in the two latter ſenſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>charity</hi> is that which the Law alms at, 'tis the ſcope of the Law, to bring us into a Love one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that we may walk in Love, that's the buſineſs of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, the Aim, the Scope of them.</p>
            <p>And then ſecondly, charity is the end of the Law, that is, 'tis the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Law, 'tis the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing end of the Law, the Law is fulfilled in Love, take it in two Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures<hi>—Rom.</hi> 13. 10. <hi>Love is the fulfilling of the Law,</hi> Love it is the Accompliſhing end of the Law, as in <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 14. <hi>The whole Law</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60602:12"/> 
               <hi>is fulfilled in one word,</hi> that's a good word Indeed—what is that one word, by which the whole Law is fulfilled? 'tis fulfilled in one word, <hi>even in this, thou ſhalt love they Neighbour as they ſelf:</hi> to them, the <hi>end</hi> here, is to be taken in that ſenſe, charity it is the accompliſhing, 'tis the fulfilling of the Law.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, One ſtep farther, what is that charity which is the end of the Commandment, both the Final end, and the fulfilling end of it? What is this charity?</p>
            <p>Charity is taken two ways in Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. More ſtrictly, as it conſiſts in the relieving of thoſe that are poor, and in the comforting of thoſe that are ſorrowful, this is charity, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the poor, to comfort the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, <hi>charity,</hi> is taken in a more large ſenſe, 'tis taken for Love in General, and ſo ſome tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate this text, the end of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60602:13"/> is Love. For <hi>charity</hi> is a word of a narrower ſenſe than <hi>Love</hi> is. The end of the Commandment is Love, and the truth is, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we render in the text, <hi>charity,</hi> doth Indifferently ſignifie, and is Indifferently tranſlated <hi>Love,</hi> or <hi>charity,</hi> all the New Teſtament over. I need not ſtay to quote places. This word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies Love to God, Love to Man.</p>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Well but what is Indeed the <hi>Charity,</hi> or <hi>Love,</hi> here Intended in the Scripture?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I anſwer, firſt, I conceive the Love here Intended, Is not love to God, though that is Love above all things, and the moſt excellent end of the Commandment, yet I conceive in this place, 'tis Charity, or Love to Man, which is here meant. And my Reaſon is this, why I reſtrain it here to the Love of Man, becauſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks of charity in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thoſe Fables, and queſtions which falſe teachers were like to raiſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60602:13"/> up in the Church. The end of the Commandment is charity, that all may be peaceable and quiet among the Brethren: and he ſaith at <hi>verſe</hi> 7. <hi>From which ſome having ſwerved,</hi> (from charity) ſhot quite beſide it, ſaith he, <hi>they are turned aſide unto vain Jangling,</hi> ſo that if we conſider either the Antecedents of the text, or the conſequents, it ſeems he confines <hi>charity,</hi> or <hi>Love</hi> here ſpoken of to that love or charity which is among men, among Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that's one thing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Charity here with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Brethren, is not that charity which doth conſiſt in opening our hand to relieve the poor, though that is a moſt excellent piece of charity, (and I pray Remember it) too pen your hand to the relieving of the poor, yet I conceive that's not the charity here meant, but the charity here meant, is charity in the uniting our hearts, and in the cloſing of our affections one with another, and then,</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60602:14"/>
               <p> Thirdly, The charity here intended, or the Love, is not a lazy habit, for one to ſay, I have a love for God, I and there it lyes and doth nothing: I ſay, the charity here intended, is not a lazy habit; but 'tis that which is put forth by vigorous and lively actings, and ſo ſome expound this Text; <hi>Charity</hi> is to be taken Metonymical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Charity,</hi> for all the offices and duties of charity, which we owe one to another.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Laſtly, As 'tis an Acting, and an active charity, which is here ſpoken of, ſo it is not every kind of charity, how vigorouſly ſoever acted, which is the end of the Commandment; but 'tis the charity that flows out from, and is fed by thoſe three ſprings ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the cloſe of the Verſe: Namely, 'tis a charity flowing out of a <hi>pure heart, a good conſcience, and faith unfeigned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot ſtay now to diſcover thoſe ſprings to you; for that would take up too much of the time. Indeed it may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60602:14"/> take up all the time, to make a little diſcovery of thoſe ſprings: All that I ſhall ſay at preſent, is only this, That the charity which iſſues out of theſe ſprings: that's the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Text; and that's the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which is the fulfilling of the Commandment. So that here we have the Genealogy (as I may call it) the Pedegree, the Parentage of Goſpel charity. Or to keep to the former Metaphor, here we have the ſpring of that bleſſed River called charity, <hi>the ſtreams whereof</hi> (like the ſtreams of the River ſpoken of, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. 4. which is the favour of God to his people) will <hi>make glad the City of God,</hi> in all the Cities of men, where ever it hath an open chanel, and a free courſe. By what hath been ſaid (beloved) you may perceive, what my work (the Lord aſſiſting) is like to be in handling this Scripture; namely, to diſcover to you that Love or Charity, which is the end of the Commandment:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60602:15"/> and chiefly indeed to diſcover to you, thoſe bleſſed ſprings, <hi>A pure heart, a good conſcience, and faith unfeigned,</hi> out of which that charity flows, and by which it muſt be fed day by day. And this will I do, if God permit.</p>
               <p>But at the preſent I ſhall wave all theſe particulars, and ſpeak to one General Point (as I hinted before) raiſed from the whole Context, and of this Verſe, or from all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of it laid together: and the Point of Doctrine is this,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>DOCT. Thoſe works of Love, of Love to man, much more of Love to God, which are the end of the Commandment, muſt flow from a good ſpring, from a gracious Principle, or a Principle of Grace.</head>
               <p>This Point is very plain in the Text, plainly collected from it. For ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Love out of a pure</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60602:15"/> 
                  <hi>heart</hi> (and the like). Now that <hi>pure heart,</hi> I ſhall ſhew clearly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards (if the Lord bring me to it) that the <hi>pure heart,</hi> is a <hi>gratious heart.</hi> So that the Love muſt flow from a principle of Grace.</p>
               <p>There are three things eſpecially in which the Completion, the full Conſtitution and making up of a good work, whether towards God or man doth conſiſt; and they muſt all three concur in the buſineſs. Evil ariſes out of any ſingle defect in that which is required: <note place="margin">Bonum oritur exi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te ra can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, malum ex q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olibet defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu.</note> But a good action muſt have a concurrence of all things requiſite thereunto. I name only theſe three.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That the work may be good, we muſt <note place="margin">What requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a good work.</note> be ſure that the matter of it be good. It muſt be good in it ſelf, as being according to Rule. And</p>
               <p>It muſt be good in the mind and in underſtanding of him that doth it:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60602:16"/> for to do that which is good, we not knowing and underſtanding it to be good, or not being perſwaded that it is good, that action is not good to us. Yea, the Apoſtle tells you, <hi>It is ſin, whatſoever is not of faith:</hi> and there he ſpeaks not of <hi>juſtifying</hi> faith, but of <hi>perſwading</hi> faith: what ever is not of faith is ſin: And 'tis poſſible for one that is in a juſtified ſtate, or one that hath juſtifying faith, yet not to do a thing with a perſwading faith, and ſo it may be ſin to him. That's one thing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The aim, or the end of the work, muſt be good; and among all ends that are good, the chief, and that which can never be left out, is the glory of God: Matth. 5. 16. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing your good works (your works of Love) may glorifie your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heaven.</hi> Not glorifie your ſelf, not ſet up ſelf. 'Twas the ſetting up of <hi>ſelf,</hi> or the making <hi>ſelf</hi> the end, which corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60602:16"/> and poiſoned all thoſe materially good, very good actions of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, even their alms giving, their praying, their faſting, as you may read at large in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 1, 5, 16. and thoſe that follow. The <hi>End</hi> doth denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the action. It muſt have a good end, elſe though the matter be never ſo good, the work is not good.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, (Which is the matter in hand:) The Principle, or ſpring of the work muſt be good: 'Tis poſſible for one to do a work that's good for the matter of it, and to have ſome good ends in it, and yet not to do it out of a right principle: and this is it which the Text and Doctrine ſpeaks, unleſs the Principle be good, the work's not good. As the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain is, ſuch are the ſtreams that come from it: As the Tree is, ſuch is the fruit that grows upon it. <hi>Do men gather Grapes of Thorns, or Figs of Thiſtles?</hi> Matth. 7. 16. Why, the Thorn hath not a Principle in Nature to put forth a Grape, the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60602:17"/> Thiſtle hath not a Principle in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to put forth a Figg; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>A corrupt Tree cannot bring forth good fruit.</hi> Which words of Chriſt, as they are prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to be underſtood concerning falſe Prophets and their Doctrine, ſo they may be truly applyed to all falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and their ends; they being corrupt, they cannot bring forth good fruit. If you would draw out of a veſſel which is unſeaſoned, or ill ſcented, the liquor will taſte of the Cask. Now we all by nature are unſeaſoned; yea, we are ill ſcented veſſels, therefore the liquor, that which paſſes from us, conſidered ſo, muſt needs have an ill ſcent, an ill taſte. And hence that cutting queſtion of Chriſt to the Phariſees, Matth. 12. 34. <hi>O Generation of Vipers, how can ye being evil, ſpeak good things?</hi> They might poſſibly ſpeak good for the matter. Bad men wil often tip their tongues with good words, and appear <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s, Golden mouth'd ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60602:17"/> when their hearts are nothing but braſs and droſs. But uſually evil men ſpeak evil; that which is evil for the matter. <hi>Their throats are an open ſepulchre, the poyſon of Aſps is under their lips,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks, quoting it from the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
               <p>And as they uſually, and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, (for that's their natural Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) ſpeak evil, ſo they always mar the good they ſpeak, either by their ill manner of ſpeaking it, or by their ill meaning in ſpeaking it. As the Devil when he made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſt, and ſaid, he was <hi>the Son of the moſt high God,</hi> it was a confeſſion like that of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> which Chriſt calls the <hi>Rock</hi> upon which the Church is built; the Devil ſpake it out of a baſe intent, and the efore Chriſt threw it away, and rebuked him for it. So evil men, they ſpoil good ſpeaking with their ill <hi>manner</hi> of ſpeaking, or their ill <hi>meaning</hi> in ſpeaking; and therefore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60602:18"/> 
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> hath that expreſſion, in <hi>Prov.</hi> 26. 7. <hi>As the leggs of the lame are not equal: ſo is a Parable in the mouth of fools.</hi> A Parable there, notes a Divine ſaying, a ruling word, a commanding word, that's a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, a word that ſhould reign over us, ſo ſaith he, a Parable, a divine ſaying, in the mouth of a fool, are like the leggs of the lame. Good words do (as it were) liſp in the mouth of a bad man, and his <hi>heart</hi> never keeps pace with his <hi>Tongue.</hi> Thus you ſee, Chriſt ſaith, evil men cannot ſpeak that which is good, they cannot ſpeak to the purpoſe fully; now as they that are evil, cannot <hi>ſpeak,</hi> ſo neither can they <hi>do</hi> good things anſwerable to the rule, or pleaſing unto God. I do not ſay, they cannot <hi>do</hi> good things, but they cannot do good things, <hi>anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the rule,</hi> or pleaſing unto God. And that's the Apoſtles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 8. after a further diſcourſe, he comes with his <hi>ſo then</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:60602:18"/> here's the concluſion, <hi>ſo then, they that are in the fleſh, they cannot pleaſe God,</hi> every action which comes up to the fulfilling of the Commandment, is pleaſing to God, but ſaith he, they that are in the fleſh, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe God;—they that are in the fleſh—what's that? ſurely not that which two Popes (as Infallible as they Judge themſelves to be,) thought to be the meaning; they thought, that by <hi>being in the fleſh,</hi> was meant being in a marriage State. But by <hi>being in the fleſh,</hi> the Apoſtle means, being in a natural, that is, being in an unregenerate State, they cannot pleaſe God, and ſuch do not only not pleaſe God when they do that which is <hi>evil,</hi> but they do not pleaſe God when they do that which is <hi>good,</hi> for the very <hi>Sacrifices of the wicked are an abomination to him,</hi> Prov. 15. 8. and therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſays of all men, in their natural capacity, or State, <hi>there is none that doth good, no not one,</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60602:19"/> 12.—Why none do good? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none of them have a principle, they have not a ſpring, though the matter they do may be good, and though poſſibly they have ſome good end in doing it, yet they not having a principle, there is none of them that doth good, that is, a compleat good, <hi>no not one,</hi> there's no excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I need not labour further in the proof of the point, but I would make ſome uſe of it, and I would make a threefold uſe out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe.</hi> The firſt may be for our Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. If thoſe good works, both to God and Man, which are the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Commandment, muſt flow from a Gratious principle, then we are Inſtructed by this truth, how to Judge of their beſt works who ſtill abide in the State of nature, having neither <hi>a pure heart,</hi> nor <hi>a good Conſcience,</hi> nor <hi>Faith unfeigned.—</hi>Why what Judgement are we to make of their works? why
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60602:19"/> ſurely they are not the end of the Commandment, they are not the fulfilling of the Commandment; the works of ſuch, even their works of charity, of love, of temperance, Patience, of Juſtice, were call'd by ſome of the godly learned Antients, <hi>ſhining ſins,</hi> and why we may not call them ſo now, I know no reaſon. That's the Judgement they give of ſuch mens good actions; for as Chriſt tells the Phariſees, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 15. that which is highly eſteemed among men, is an Abomination unto God. Why? becauſe it wants this principle. And to be ſure, though their box of ointment, I mean the good things done by Perſons who have not theſe principles, I ſay though their box of ointment may have a fragrant ſmell among many men, yet there are many dead flies in it, eſpecially one great one, call'd unbelief, which makes their whole box of ointment very unſavory in the noſtrils of God, for ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60602:20"/> 
                  <hi>without faith it is Impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi> And that's one of the ſprings expreſly ſpoken of in the text; Goſpel charity is of a nobler extract than to be found in the whole compaſs of nature, and Godlineſs moves in a higher ſphere than the beſt dreſs that the gayeſt Moraliſt ever reacht unto. In <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 20. <hi>Except your Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs exceed the Righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, ye ſhall in no wiſe enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> That's a word for Information.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe.</hi> 2. Now upon that, let me take up a ſecond uſe by way of Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. If this be a truth, then 'tis to be Lamented that the Religious duties, and charitable Acts of many who bear the name of Chriſt, flow meerly from a natural principle, and doing ſo, they are not the fulfilling of the Commandment. The moſt of men Love one another with affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction no more ſpiritual than <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Pithius,</hi> and <hi>Pilades</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60602:20"/> or any other who are moſt memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed, or admired among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens for Love. Yea I may ſay, they worſhip God and Jeſus Chriſt with a devotion no more raiſed, and ſpiritual, than the old <hi>Romans</hi> did worſhip their <hi>Jupiter,</hi> or the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> their great Godeſs <hi>Diana.</hi> And ſurely this is to be Lamented, that Chriſtian Acts ſhould be done, and not from a principle ſpiritual, or not from a Chriſtian principle. It is very poſſible, and very ordinary to follow Chriſt, yea to call upon Chriſt, meerly with human affections, with Carnal affections. Jeſus Chriſt did find it ſo. In <hi>John</hi> 6. 26. <hi>Ye ſeek me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>not becauſe ye ſaw the Miracles, but becauſe ye did eat of the loves and were filled.</hi> To follow Chriſt, was an excellent work, but they did it meerly upon a humane principle. Yea, that prayer of theirs in <hi>Verſe</hi> 34. may well be Judged to come meerly from a carnal ſpirit. When Chriſt had diſcourſe of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60602:21"/> bread that came down from Heaven, and giveth life into the World, ſay they, <hi>Lord, evermore give us of this bread,</hi> and yet this was but from a Carnal deſire, not knowing what that bread meant ſpiritually. And it appears clearly to be ſo, for in the cloſe of the Chapter, many of his Hearers went quite away, they forſook him. Now certainly to do theſe excellent things, and to do them but with Carnal principles, this is a thing to be Lamented. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> doth report it as a thing to be lamented, that often in this world it is done to good men according to the works of the wicked, and it's done to wicked men, according to the works of the righteous: <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8. 14. This is a thing to be lamented, but I now ſhall ſhew you two ſights more, much more to be lamented.</p>
               <p>Firſt, 'Tis a very lamentable thing to ſee good men do according to the works of the wicked. Thus did <hi>David</hi> in the matter of <hi>Uriah,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60602:21"/> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. Thus did <hi>Solomon,</hi> when his heart went after ſtrange Gods, and he built High Places to their Abominations, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. 4, 5. Thus did <hi>Aſa,</hi> a good King, when he impriſoned the Prophet, and in his diſeaſe ſought to the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and not to God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. 10, 12. Yea, thus did St. <hi>Peter</hi> that holy Apoſtle, when he deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yea, forſwore his Maſter, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 72, 74. And thus have many other godly men done, under the preſſures of Temptation and Corruption. And is not this a ſad ſight, to ſee one profeſſing Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, yea, one that is really godly, act thus like a wicked man? This is to act (as I have ſometimes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt it) the old Creatures part, in the new Creatures ſtate. This is a very ſad thing.</p>
               <p>I, but now I have another ſight to ſhew you, according to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure of this Text and Doctrine, which is very ſad alſo. And what's
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60602:22"/> that? Why, to ſee bad men do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the works of good men, ſtill continuing in their bad ſtate. They plod on, and go on doing good things, but never mind to become good themſelves: And ſo bad men do according to the works of the righteous: I ſay, This is a ſad ſight. And thus did <hi>Saul,</hi> when he was among the Prophets: There was a bad man doing good things, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. And thus did <hi>Ahab,</hi> when he humbled himſelf; a wicked man do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a very good thing, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. Thus did <hi>Jehu,</hi> when he deſtroyed Idolatry: A very good work, but a very bad man, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10. 28. Thus did <hi>Judas,</hi> when he preacht the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; a very good work, but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Traytor. And thus did <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> when he profeſt the Goſpel, and followed the Apoſtles: A very good work, but himſelf an hypocrite, and a lover of the world. And thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed do all hypocrites, and meer formaliſts, in their performing of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60602:22"/> Goſpel worſhip. And thus Chriſt will tell them at the laſt day, as he ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 22, 23. when they came upon him ſo to upbraid him (as it were) with the good things which they had done. <hi>We have propheſied in thy name, we have caſt out Devils in thy Name; we have done many good and mighty works in thy Name;</hi> Saith Chriſt to them, <hi>Depart from me ye workers of iniquity.</hi> Though you did theſe good things, yet you never did them from a ſound principle, from a principle of Grace: No, you your ſelves were ſecret workers, or lovers of iniquity, while you did all theſe good things. Now is not this a ſad ſight? I confeſs, it is a ſad ſight, to ſee a bad man do that which is bad, or a wicked man to do that which is wicked; yet I ſay, it is a ſadder ſight to ſee a bad man continuing in his ſtate, having no ſpiritual principles, to go on do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good: For what is this, but the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60602:23"/> juſt contrary to what I ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This is the acting of the new Creatures part in the old Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſtate; and what will that avail?</p>
               <p>And I would ſay theſe two things further.</p>
               <p>God often declares himſelf very highly againſt ſuch as do good, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves continuing evil. He declares himſelf weary of their ſervices, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when there is hypocriſie in them. Iſa. 1. 14. Prov. 21. 27. <hi>The ſacrifice of the wicked is abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how much more when he bringeth it with a wicked mind?</hi> That is, when he brings it for baſe ends, hoping by his ſacrifice to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God for his ſin. Some hope by their good works to turn away the wrath of God; and they hope to get Heaven by their good prayers, and by their alms (and the like). I ſay, when a man doth a good thing, with ſuch an evil mind as this, hoping to ſatisfie the Juſtice of God, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60602:23"/> turn away his wrath by his doings; this is now abomination to God. Or when he hopes that God will be well pleaſed with him, in that he brings him a ſacrifice, doth him ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſervice, though he goes on in his ſin. Theſe are thoſe the Lord doth ſo often proteſt againſt.</p>
               <p>And I would ſay to them further: The good you do in that ſtate, not having a ſpiritual Principle, the good that you do will not profit you, 'twill not advantage you; 'twill be no plea in the great day. All the profit you can have by it at moſt, when you have had the utmoſt that it comes to, it is but ſome external or outward mercy. As <hi>Ahab,</hi> he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf: why, he had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for it; he had his penny: and therefore ſaith the Lord, <hi>Seeſt thou how</hi> Ahab <hi>humbleth himſelf? The Judgement ſhall not come in his dayes.</hi> A deliverance from an outward Judgement: but here was no delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from wrath, and from eternal
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60602:24"/> Judgement. And ſo <hi>Jehu,</hi> for the good works that he did, he had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what; but alas, what was it? Indeed a great thing in the eyes of the world, a Kingdom; and a Kingdom for ſeveral Generations. But the truth is, A poor thing, for that was all indeed he had for his zeal in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Idolatry. He had the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for four Genenerations; but he abiding a wicked man, while he did that good thing, himſelf was cut off for ever. And you ſee the Ruler in <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 21. who came to Chriſt, and told him, how he had done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the matters of the Law: why, Jeſus Chriſt ſaw indeed he had done them, but he knew he had not done them from a right principle; and therefore what was it that Chriſt gave him? Saith he, <hi>he beheld him, and loved him.</hi> A love of pity, as ſome expound the place. O it's a pity that ſuch a perſon as thou art, that thou haſt been a keeper of the Law, yet haſt not done it upon a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60602:24"/> right principle. And that he did not, it is plain; for when Chriſt put him home he went away ſorrowful. Now all that he had for it, Chriſt gave him ſome approbation: and as he did to that other in Mark 12. 34. <hi>Thou art not far from the Kingdom of God.</hi> I, but he was ſo far, as he ſhould never come there, unleſs he changed his ſtate. So that I ſay, The Condition of thoſe that do good things, not out of a good principle, is indeed very lamentable, upon theſe and many other accounts.</p>
               <p>But poſſibly you will ſay, If it be ſo, That they who do good, not out of a right principle, their work will not turn to their profit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their caſe is to be lamented. If it be ſo, Were it not beſt to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe thoſe who yet remain unconvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to forbear doing good till them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are better?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, No, by no means. We give no ſuch advice in the matter: but let all men do all the good they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60602:25"/> can. And I would exhort the worſt of men to do good: To hear the Word preacht, to pray, to give alms. <hi>Daniel</hi> gave that counſel to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> a Heathen King, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 27. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> gave that counſel to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> whom he ſaw to be <hi>in the gaul of bitterneſs, and in the bonds of iniquity.</hi> And that the good that he had done, his receiving Baptiſm, and outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith, it was ſo far from coming from a good principle, that he was in the very gall of bitterneſs; yet ſaith he, pray, if it may be, thy ſins may be forgiven thee. Though men are evil, yet let them do good as far as they can: and I would ſay theſe three things about it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, They are under an obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to do good. For mans inability to perform a duty rightly, doth not take off the obligation which is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to perform it. And though a bad man ſins in his manner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, yet his refuſing to do it, would be more ſinful.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60602:25"/>
               <p> And I would ſay further, Though he pleaſe not God in doing it, yet he diſpleaſes God in not doing it: So that indeed, man naturally conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or in his fallen ſtate, is fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a very ſad <hi>Dilemma.</hi> If he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to do good, he ſins. If he doth good, he ſpoils it in the doing of it. But notwithſtanding all this (I ſay) I am far from diſcouraging the worſt of men to do good, or to adviſe any to forbear to do good. No, I would convince all, that their preſent ſtate is bad; and exhort all to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to all means whereby them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may be made better. And that's the third Uſe which I ſhall briefly make of this point, and ſo I ſhall conclude.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 3. Is it ſo, That thoſe good works that flow from a good Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are pleaſing to God? Why then we ſee the neceſſity of Regeneration. Chriſt ſaith in 3 John 3. <hi>Verily, verily.</hi> There's a ſtrong and a double
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60602:26"/> aſſeveration: <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, except a man be born again, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God.</hi> We are not born with this <hi>pure heart,</hi> with this <hi>good conſcience,</hi> with this <hi>faith unfeigned,</hi> which are the requiſites to a <hi>good work</hi> in the Text. We are not born with theſe: for <hi>Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean? Not one.</hi> Not one among the ſons of men. Job 14. 4. <hi>A pure heart,</hi> a good conſcience, faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned, are the iſſues of the new birth. <hi>Education</hi> cannot make the heart pure; It muſt be <hi>Revelation</hi> which makes the heart pure. Good Education it may change the Life and the Converſation. As they ſay, To ſtudy Arts and Philoſophy, it takes off the roughneſs that is in mans nature, <note place="margin">-didiciſſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliter d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes Emollit mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</note> and doth ſmooth them, and frame them very much for excellent uſes. Good literature and education, it may civilize, but it cannot ſpiritualize:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60602:26"/> It may change a mans courſe, but it cannot change his nature, that's only done by Regeneration. Now I ſay, a mans ſtate, his nature muſt be changed; he muſt have a pure heart, which we never have till our natures are changed. He muſt <hi>be</hi> good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can <hi>do</hi> good ſpiritually. Mark that word of the Apoſtle, Epheſ. 2. 10. <hi>We are his workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, which God hath before ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that we ſhould walk in them.</hi> Mark it, here are good works. But how do we come to theſe good works? Why, <hi>We are his workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> ſaith he, we are his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. God works us, before we can work for him: he makes us good, before we can do good. Saith he, <hi>We are his workmanſhip.</hi> And then, created, or ſo created in Chriſt Jeſus to good works. We by union to Jeſus Chriſt, come to have a ſpiritual prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to carry us out in the doing of all good works. Here's your way.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60602:27"/> You muſt be Gods workmanſhip, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can do Gods work: You muſt be new creatures, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can do them.</p>
               <p>A Crab-tree will never yield plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant fruit, untill you change the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it. Take a Crab-tree and plant it in the beſt ſoil that you have, and water it, and dreſs it, and prune it as much as you can, yet this Crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree will bear nothing but Crabs, ſowre fruit, till you come to graft it; and then your grafting of it, doth change the nature of the ſtock, and it hath another principle, and ſo then it brings forth good fruit. So it is in this caſe. Take the beſt natured man in the world plant him in the beſt ſoil, in the beſt ground, in Church-ground, plant him in the houſe of God, and there let him be watered by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain of holy Doctrine, and let him be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t and cultivated eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing forth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, nothing but unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60602:27"/> fruit, till he himſelf be changed. Though he be under all thoſe ſpiritual means, yet till thoſe means have wrought effectually in him, his actions are all unſavoury. 'Tis only by our implantation into Jeſus Chriſt, that we become fit to do good, ſo as is acceptable unto God. 'Tis this that makes the change. For as in nature, the graft doth change the ſtock; ſo in grace, the ſtock doth change the grafted branch. As we are grafted into Chriſt, he changes the branch; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing planted into Chriſt, by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Spirit, we are then made like him; and then we bring forth fruits of righteouſneſs, which are to the glory of God <hi>by him.</hi> Mark the expreſſion, <hi>Being filled with the fruits of righteouſneſs, which are by Chriſt.</hi> That is, by vertue of union with Chriſt, of implantation and ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into Chriſt. When once it is thus, then all your fruits are ſweet fruit, and pleaſant fruit, it is well
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60602:28"/> taſted. Why, it is done Firſt, From a principle of life in Chriſt. And Secondly, It is done from a principle of Love unto Chriſt: and then when your works, whether reſpecting God or man are thus done, then they are the fulfilling, and the final end of the Commandment. For then they come from the pure heart. Of which hereafter (if God will, I may ſpeak). And ſo much at the preſent of the point in General, That until there be a good Principle, there cannot be a good work.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60602:28"/>
            <head>SERMON II.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Jan.</hi> 6. 1672.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 TIM. 1. 5.</bibl>
               <q>Now the end of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is Charity, out of a pure heart, and of a good Conſcience, and of Faith unfeigned.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HAving ſhewed that every good work which is to anſwer to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, muſt flow from a good ſpring,</p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to ſpeak of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60602:29"/> ſprings from whence they flow. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with that which is firſt in the Text, <hi>A pure heart.</hi> The end of the Commandment, is charity, <hi>out of a pure heart.</hi> A <hi>pure heart</hi> is the point I am now to ſpeak to, and the matter I am to make diſcovery about. It being in order, in this Text, the firſt of thoſe three moſt bleſſed ſprings, out of which all duties well pleaſing unto God muſt proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A pure heart.</hi> Two things are here to be ſpoken to.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What is meant by <hi>heart.</hi> And,</p>
            <p>Secondly, What by purity of heart: And ſo put both together, <hi>A pure heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt I need not ſtay to ſpend time to ſhew you, what is meant by the <hi>heart:</hi> It being that which you have ſo often heard.</p>
            <p>By <hi>heart,</hi> the Scripture often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the whole inner man.</p>
            <p>And ſometimes it intends ſome
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60602:29"/> ſpecial faculties of the inner man. The <hi>underſtanding</hi> is noted by the <hi>heart;</hi> the <hi>will</hi> by the <hi>heart;</hi> the <hi>affections</hi> by the <hi>heart;</hi> the <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> by the <hi>heart.</hi> And in this large ſenſe we are to take the word <hi>heart</hi> here: only bating the reference of it unto <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which is ſpoken of as the ſecond diſtinct ſpring from whence good actions flow.</p>
            <p>The <hi>heart</hi> then here, is the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> the <hi>will,</hi> the <hi>affections.</hi> Indeed what ever lyes in the boſome of man, you may call his <hi>heart.</hi> Yet I ſhall not proſecute the point in this diſtinctneſs of theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar faculties of the ſoul; ſhewing how the <hi>underſtanding</hi> is pure, which is by its freedome from error, and clear light in divine truths. How the <hi>Will</hi> is pure, which is, by its freedom from the bondage, from the obſtinacy and rebellion, which doth naturally, wholly poſſeſs it: and by having a freedome in chooſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, and refuſing that which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60602:30"/> is evil. Nor ſhall I ſtay ſtrictly to ſhew what the purity of the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions is; namely, their freedom from all inordinacy and irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, either as to the object upon which they are fixt; or as to the meaſure and degree in which they are fixt upon thoſe objects.</p>
            <p>That which I ſhall do indeed, ſhall be to ſpeak to the <hi>Heart,</hi> and ſo of the purity of it in a general notion, as it concerns the whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner man.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>heart</hi> as to <hi>purity,</hi> may be conſidered two wayes,</p>
            <p>Firſt, As Made,</p>
            <p>Secondly, As Re-made.</p>
            <p>The <hi>heart</hi> of man as made, was pure; I mean, in its primitive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. So <hi>Adam</hi> had a pure heart; his <hi>underſtanding</hi> pure, his <hi>will</hi> pure, his <hi>affections</hi> pure. God made him upright; but he loſt his pure heart, or the purity of his heart. Sin did impure his whole inner man; and he being our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60602:30"/> loſt purity of heart, not only for himſelf, but for us. All mankind loſt that <hi>made</hi> purity of heart when <hi>Adam</hi> fell. And therefore the very firſt Complaint which the Lord made of the Fallen World, was concerning the pravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and impurity of their hearts, in Gen. 6. 5. <hi>God ſaw that the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of man was great in the earth,</hi> [that's wickedneſs of Life,] <hi>and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was only evil continually.</hi> By this we ſee to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, That the firſt <hi>made</hi> purity of the heart was loſt. Here are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particulars ſetting forth the evil of mans heart, as plainly ſhews, that it is nothing but evil. Here's the evil of his <hi>Imaginations,</hi> The Imagination of the <hi>Thoughts</hi> of his heart. And not here and there one, but <hi>every</hi> imagination of the thoughts of his heart, it was <hi>evil.</hi> And not evil with ſome mixture of good, but purely evil. It was evil with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60602:31"/> any goodneſs in it: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith he <hi>Only evil.</hi> Nor was it in this impure ſtate, only for a <hi>fit,</hi> or now and then: but ſaith the Text, <hi>Continually</hi> evil; or as the Hebrew is, <hi>every day.</hi> Day by day, which we render <hi>Continually.</hi> So that now the <hi>made</hi> pure heart was loſt; and no man hath a pure heart by nature; nor hath any man a heart leſs impure by nature, than another man hath. Our hearts in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are all of a make; and that's ſtark naught. So ſpake the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremy</hi> likewiſe in <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 10. The heart of man is deceitful <hi>above all things.</hi> The heart of man is the greateſt cheat in the world, and the greateſt Impoſtor in the world: and ſaith he, 'tis <hi>deſperately wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> and 'tis ſo wicked, that the wickedneſs of it is beyond Humane Comprehenſion: The wickedneſs of it is beyond the knowledge of man; <hi>who knows it?</hi> Neither he that hath the heart, nor any other that ſees
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60602:31"/> him that hath it, knows how wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the heart of man is. And pray take notice, That the Prophet doth not ſpeak there of ſome ſort of vile, baſe, debauched, wicked men, whoſe hearts were ſo deceitful and wicked; but he ſpeaks of men in general, as they are in nature: And much of that deceitfulneſs and wickedneſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, even when they are in Grace. We may therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, (at leaſt in this matter) alluding to that of <hi>Solomon</hi> in the <hi>Proverbs, Chap.</hi> 27. 19. <hi>As in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, face anſwereth to face; ſo the heart of man to man.</hi> There are ſome that do trouble the water in that Text, with various Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I ſhall not ſtay upon them. But all that I alledge the Text for, is to ſhew, That look what there is in one mans heart naturally, the ſame is in anothers. Juſt as he that looks into the water; the face in the water upon which he looks, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers his own face looking into it: So
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60602:32"/> doth the heart of man to man. The hearts of all good men, of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons regenerate, do anſwer one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the main. Look what the heart of one godly man is, the ſame is the heart of another godly man in the main, though there may be particular differences. And ſo, take all men in their natural condition. Look what the heart of one man is, the ſame is the heart of another; and all ſtark naught. So then, there's now no pure heart in nature. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>made</hi> pure heart is loſt, we muſt then conſider the <hi>heart</hi> as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made pure.</p>
            <p>Here is a pure heart in the Text: 'Tis a heart re-made pure. A heart made pure by a gracious Reſtitution. And mark it, I ſay, it is a heart <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made.</hi> It is not a heart <hi>mended;</hi> that will not ſerve the turn. The heart of man received ſuch a crack in the fall, that there is no mending of it: It muſt be new made. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay, the pure heart is a heart
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60602:32"/> re-made, new made. As we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſay of a Bell, if a Bell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a crack, there is no mending of it: You cannot mend a Bell, as you may mend a Braſs Pan, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a piece to it: There is no way to mend a crackt Bell, but by new caſting it; it muſt to the Founder. Truly thus it is with mans heart; there is no mending it, no putting a patch to it; no repairing it, as you may repair a houſe that is delapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated. No, it muſt be new made: and therefore the pure heart which is here ſpoken of in the Text, in other Texts is called <hi>a new heart,</hi> Ezek. 36. 25, 26. It is not a <hi>mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> heart, but it is a <hi>new heart. I will take away the heart of ſtone.</hi> The former heart is an <hi>heart of ſtone;</hi> a heart that hath no more of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe in it; no more of ſoftneſs or tenderneſs in it, than a ſtone: I will <hi>take away</hi> the heart of ſtone. He doth not ſay, I will <hi>mend</hi> the heart of ſtone, but I will <hi>take it away.</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:60602:33"/> That is, I will take away the heart, ſo far as it is ſtony; <hi>And I will give you an heart of fleſh:</hi> that is, a <hi>new heart,</hi> an heart of fleſh. The <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made</hi> heart is a heart made wholly new: It is made wholly new by the power of God; and I may give it you in theſe four things.</p>
            <p>This <hi>pure heart,</hi> of which I am ſpeaking, is purified or made new.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Meritoriouſly by the blood of Chriſt. For it is by <hi>blood</hi> that things are purified and purged; as the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe at large, eſpecially in the ninth Chapter of the Epiſtle, Ver. 22. <hi>Almoſt all things are by the Law purged with blood; and without ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood is no Remiſſion.</hi> The heart is made pure,</p>
            <p>Firſt, By the blood of Chriſt, that cleanſing blood: <hi>The blood of Chriſt cleanſeth from all ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It is purified or made pure, by the Spirit of Chriſt; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60602:33"/> we find theſe two put together, 1 Pet 1. 2. <hi>Through ſanctification of the Spirit unto obedience, and ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> As we are purified through the ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the blood of Jeſus Chriſt; ſo through the ſanctification of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. The Spirit is pure, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is a purifier. The Spirit is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>water:</hi> the Spirit is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>fire,</hi> that purifies, that fetches out the droſs and the filth, and makes all pure. And indeed, the impurity which is in the heart of man, is ſuch, as nothing leſs than the blood of Chriſt, and therefore <hi>of the Spirit</hi> can purge it out. The fire of <hi>afflictions</hi> will not purge out the impurities of the heart. The fire of <hi>Hell</hi> will not fetch out the droſs that is in the hearts of the damned. Nothing but the blood of Chriſt, nothing but the Spirit of Chriſt, are able to do it. The blood of Chriſt meritoriouſly, the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60602:34"/> Spirit efficiently, and efficaciouſly. And then,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The heart re-made pure, is ſo made <hi>Inſtrumentally</hi> by the <hi>Word. The Word of God is pure, it is as Silver purified in the fire ſeven times.</hi> And the Word of God is a purifier inſtrumentally; and the uſual way by which the heart is <hi>re-made</hi> pure, is by the Word. Chriſt ſaith, John 15. 3. <hi>Ye are clean:</hi> How? <hi>Through the Word that I have ſpoken.</hi> And in general, the Apoſtle in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 22, 26. ſaith, That Jeſus Chriſt doth ſanctifie and cleanſe his Church, <hi>with the waſhing of water, by the Word.</hi> With the waſhing of water, that is, with the Spirit. But what's the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument? <hi>By the Word.</hi> This way is purity of heart commonly and uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally wrought by the Word. And,</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The heart is made pure applicatorily by Faith, Acts 15. 9. <hi>He put no difference between us and them</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) that is,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60602:34"/> between <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> having <hi>purified their hearts by faith.</hi> God works faith in the heart, and then faith purifies the heart by applying the blood of Chriſt, and by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Spirit, and by working the ſoul to a ſubmiſſion to the holy <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Will</hi> of God. So that thus in theſe wayes the heart is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made pure: and of this re-made pure heart, it is that the Text ſpeaks. That's the ſpring out of which holy and acceptable works to the Lord doth flow.</p>
            <div type="object">
               <head>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſome may ſay, Is there any ſuch thing as a pure heart? We find thoſe queſtions ſomewhat rife in the Book of Job, <hi>What is man, that he ſhould be clean?</hi> So in Chap. 15. 14. <hi>Or how can he be clean, that is born of a woman?</hi> Chap. 25. 4. And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, in Prov. 20. 9. <hi>Who can ſay, I have made my heart clean, I am pure from my ſin?</hi> It is plain then by theſe Scriptures, that there
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60602:35"/> is no ſuch thing as a pure heart.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer briefly, in three things to theſe Scriptures, and to all Scriptures of a like Import. When the Scripture ſpeaks thus, It doth teach us, either,</p>
               <p>Firſt, that no man is born with a pure heart; or it teaches us,</p>
               <p>Secondly, That no man by his own power hath made his heart pure; or,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it teaches us that no heart is made pure in this world with an abſolutely perfect purity. Indeed the beſt purity which the heart at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to in this world, hath a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of much impurity in it: ſo that thus indeed there is no heart pure. That is, there is no heart <hi>Legally</hi> pure, <hi>ſtrictly</hi> pure; but there are thouſands of hearts through Grace, that are ſincerely pure, that are <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lically</hi> pure, and ſo eſteemed in the thoughts of God, and ſo expreſt in his word.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall ſay, you tell us there
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60602:35"/> is an Evangelical purity, what mean you by it? when may the heart be ſaid to be Evangelically pure?</p>
               <p>I anſwer thus, the heart is Evangelically <note place="margin">When the heart may be ſaid to be Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally pure.</note> pure, though there be ſin dwelling in us, or an in-dwelling ſin, and though ſin is ſtirring, hath ſtrong motions in us, makes war in our ſouls from day to day, though ſin doth ſome times prevail, and give us that foil; yet notwithſtanding all this, when,</p>
               <p>Firſt, the ſoul in free from the Command of every ſin,</p>
               <p>Secondly, When the ſoul is freed from the cuſtomary practice of every ſin; and,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, When the ſoul is free from the love of any ſin, then the ſoul is Evangelically pure. Indeed ſin will hide, ſin will ſtirr, and I cannot warrant any man in the world, that is a man of the pureſt heart in the world, but that his ſin may
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60602:36"/> poſſibly give him a foil. But this is certain, he that hath an Evangelical purity, is free from the commanding power of ſin, and from that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and cuſtomary practice of ſin; and from the love of ſin. A man of a pure heart, may have a ſpecial ſin, that is, a ſin to which he is more inclined than to any other. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times through the conſtitution of his body, ſometimes through his occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and in the way of his calling; there are many things which do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger men to ſome ſpecial ſin, now though I ſay a good man may have a ſpecial ſin, a ſin that he finds his heart moſt running out after, in which ſenſe <hi>David</hi> call's ſome ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, <hi>his Iniquity,</hi> Pſal. 111. 23. <hi>I have kept my ſelf</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>from mine Iniquity,</hi> that is, from the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity that did moſt beſet him. A good man then, may have a ſpecial ſin, which haunts him, which dogs him, and beſets him, but yet he hath not a <hi>beloved</hi> ſin; Evangelical
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60602:36"/> purity, and the <hi>love</hi> of ſin, cannot conſiſt together, he that hath a pure heart, cannot play with his ſin, cannot ſport with his ſin, cannot take content in thinking of ſin, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſt, or what may be to come. As they in the Prophet, <hi>this day is thus with us, and to morrow ſhall be more abundant.</hi> No, he cannot pleaſe himſelf thus, in reference to any ſin. So that I conclude it, the pure heart is freed, (if he be Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelically freed) from ſin in all theſe notions, and ſo he is the Perſon here meant in the text, from whom all holy actions may proceed accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to the Lord; and that may ſerve for the opening of this point, for I intend to diſpatch it at this time.</p>
               <p>I ſhall make ſome uſe of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe.</hi> Firſt, To ſtir up all to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether they have this pure heart yea or no. You ſee the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of it, it is one of the ſprings out of which every action that is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60602:37"/> pleaſing to God, according to his appointment muſt flow, therefore it ſtands us much upon, leſt we looſe all things that we work, To have a good aſſurance in our own boſoms, that we have a pure heart in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms; and we had need conſider it. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, 'tis moſt ſure that many think they have pure hearts, and have them not. <hi>Solomon</hi> hath an expreſſion; ſaith he, <hi>there are a Generation that are pure in their own own eyes, and yet are not cleanſed from their wickedneſs,</hi> Chap. 30. 12. It's an eaſie matter to be pure in our own eyes, and yet remain altogether unclean? <hi>A Generation pure in their own eyes.</hi> And St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſpeaks of a ſort of people; who would needs be called <hi>Cathoriſts,</hi> and (ſaith he) they do <hi>call themſelves</hi> ſo, they moſt proudly, and odiouſly call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the pure ones. But accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his diſcovery of them, they were not cleanſed from their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60602:37"/> and how many are thus indeed, clean in their own eyes, and yet are unclean. And,</p>
               <p>Secondly, There are many that are clean, not only in their own eyes, but in the eyes of other men, yea poſſibly in very good men, Godly men, clean in their eyes, and yet for all this, they are not cleanſed from their filthneſs. Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt detecting the hypocriſy of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> ſaith, that they were like <hi>whited ſepulchers, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear fair to men, but within are full of dead mens bones, and rottenneſs.</hi> Thus it is with many, very many in the world, they appear very beautiful, like a brave ſepulcher, painted, and gilded, have poſſibly a very pure <hi>hand,</hi> you can ſee no evil they do; they have poſſibly a very pure <hi>Tongue,</hi> you can hear of no evil they <hi>ſpeak.</hi> Speak even as they in <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 28, 29. of whom the Lord ſaith, <hi>they have well ſaid in all that they have ſpoken,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60602:38"/> they have well done indeed, in all that they have ſpoken? I but they did little of that which they had ſpoken. Many are very good in the ſight of other Men, but not ſo in the ſight of God, he doth eaſily diſcover their Impurities, and let me tell you, their are many that diſcover their own Impurity, and of whom we may conclude, that they have no pure heart, while we conſider the groſs Impurities of their lives. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſome carry it cloſely, and others profainly, and as the Lord ſpeaks in <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 34. <hi>Their ſin is in their skirts,</hi> you need not dig for it, ſaith, God; <hi>I have not found it by ſecret ſearching,</hi> or by digging, their ſin is in their skirts. It is ſo with many, their ſin is in their skirts, and you need not dig to find it out, the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of their life do plainly ſhew the impurity of their hearts. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micha</hi> puts the queſtion, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Shall I count them pure with the wicked ballances, and with the</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60602:38"/> 
                  <hi>bag of deceithful weights?</hi> ſhall I count them pure? do you think he hath a good heart, who hath ſuch a life as this, willing to deceive, and willing to wrong his Brethren, or thoſe that he deals with? ſo we may carry on the Prophets chiding que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to many and many. Shall we count them pure whoſe eyes are full of Adultery? Shall we count them pure whoſe hands are full of blood? Shall we count them pure whoſe houſes are full of oppreſſion? Shall we think them pure whoſe mouths are full of curſing and oaths, of ſcurility? Shall we count them pure whoſe mouths and Tongues are often tipt with ſcofs againſt purity? why the impurity of theſe mens hearts breaks out, <hi>the ſhew of their countenance doth teſtifie againſt them,</hi> that <hi>they declare their ſin as</hi> Sodom, <hi>they hide it not.</hi> You ſee then there are a number that want this purity of heart. Conſider them firſt, who are pure in their own eyes, and have
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60602:39"/> great thoughts of their own purity. Conſider, ſecondly; thoſe that have a great opinion for purity among men, they appear to others ſo, and yet the Lord ſees they are not ſo. And then, if you go abroad to the profain world, who proclaim their impurities, and glory in their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity. And therefore to urge that a little further,</p>
               <p>How may we know where there is purity of heart, that Evangelical purity which I ſpake of before? In opening the words, take a few touches as to the diſcovery of a pure heart.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he that Indeed hath a pure heart, is very <note place="margin">Diſcoveries of a pure heart.</note> ſenſible that once he had an impure heart, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>In ſin was I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and brought forth in Iniquity. David</hi> was a man of a pure heart. He was very ſenſible that once his heart was very impure. And,</p>
               <p>Secondly, He that hath a pure heart is ſenſible that to this day there
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60602:39"/> remains much impurity in his heart, and the purer any ones heart is, the more doth he mourn under his heart impurities. And,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, He that hath a pure heart, loves every thing that is pure, and the more pure it is, the more he loves it, the more he approves it. Here's a pure heart; <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 10. <hi>He approves the things that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent.</hi> Things that <hi>differ,</hi> ſo the word is. That is, things that differ in a way of <hi>excellency,</hi> not only things that differ, as <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>bad</hi> differ, but things that differ as <hi>good</hi> and <hi>good</hi> differ; for there's a <hi>gradual</hi> difference between good and good, as there is a <hi>ſpecifical</hi> difference between good and evil; as there is a difference between wheat and cockle, ſo there is a difference between wheat &amp; wheat: As there is a difference between Gold and Copper, ſo there is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Gold and Gold. There's the Gold of Ophyr, the moſt pure
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60602:40"/> Gold. Now I ſay, he that hath a pure heart, he loves all that is pure, and the more pure any thing is, the more he loves it. That's the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Apoſtle, he approves things that differ in a way of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, not only as good differs from evil, but as one good differs from another. If there be any thing which is more excellent than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he is for that. Here's your pure heart then. And,</p>
               <p>Fourthly, A pure heart will be full of pure thoughts, or you will be ſure that no impure thoughts ſhall have any welcome in you; a pure heart converſes chiefly with God in purity of thoughts, and good thoughts; as the <hi>wicked</hi> are diſcribed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. to be ſuch <hi>as have not God in all their thoughts,</hi> they have not the pure God, nor the holy God in all there thoughts, that is, God is not at all in their thoughts to any purpoſe. So we may ſay of the pure heart, God
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60602:40"/> is in all his thoughts, or he would fain have his thoughts always upon God. And ſo thoſe that the Lord accounts his Jewels are diſcribed, <hi>Mal.</hi> 13. 16. Saith he, I will deal thus and thus with them that fear me, and that <hi>think upon my name.</hi> Mark, that <hi>think</hi> upon my name. A great part of our ſpiritual purity, is to the often <hi>thinking upon the pure</hi> God: The pure heart (I ſay) is often full of pure thoughts, and you may take meaſure of the purity of your hearts very much, by conſidering what your thoughts are. And,</p>
               <p>Fifthly, your heart is full of pure and good deſires, <hi>thoughts</hi> and ſingle acts and puttings forth of the ſoul upon ſuch and ſuch objects and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but <hi>deſires</hi> they are wrought up into ſuch or ſuch a ſpecial point: a pure heart is full of good deſires, and eſpecially he deſires to be more good, to be better, he deſires to know more of God, and to honour
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60602:41"/> God more, he deſires to enjoy God more, he hungers and thirſts after God. And what's the hunger and thirſt of the ſoul? 'Tis ſpiritual deſire: <hi>deſire</hi> is the hunger and thirſt of the ſoul. Now a pure heart is full of theſe deſires, and theſe are the moſt ſpiritual diſcoveries of him that hath a pure heart. Let him conſider what his deſires are, what he would have: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. <hi>With my ſoul have I deſired thee.</hi> Mark your deſires. And then,</p>
               <p>Sixthly, If you you have this pure heart, you will not only have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pure deſires, but you will have purpoſes, pure reſolves, you will be full of good reſolves, and by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves the heart is fixt, faſtened, ſettled, reſolution is the ſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſoul; now a pure heart is full of pure reſolves, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. The reſolves and purpoſes are of two kinds.</p>
               <p>Firſt, He purpoſes and reſolves
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60602:41"/> to adhere and cleave to that which is good. Thus he doth reſolve with himſelf, fall back, fall edge, let the winds blow high or low, this I am reſolved, this is my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to cleave to Chriſt, and that which is good, as that good man <hi>Barnabas</hi> is ſaid to exhort the people, <hi>Acts.</hi> 11. 23. <hi>He exhorted them, that with purpoſe of heart they would cleave to the Lord, with purpoſe of heart.</hi> Holy purpoſes they are are as the Glew, by which our hearts are faſtened to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I exhort you with purpoſe of heart that you would cleave to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And then there is a purpoſe in a pure heart, againſt all that is evil, againſt all that is Impure: <hi>Daniel</hi> 1. That holy man <hi>Daniel, Verſe</hi> 8. ſaith the Text, <hi>Daniel purpoſed in his heart, that he would not defile himſelf</hi> with the portion of the Kings meat; he was reſolved
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60602:42"/> of that, now he hath a pure heart indeed, who purpoſes that he will never defile himſelf, his <hi>heart,</hi> nor his <hi>life</hi> neither. And indeed, ſuch purpoſes have they that have pure hearts, of one kind or of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Yea ſometimes we find holy ones heigthening their purpoſes to <hi>vows,</hi> yea to <hi>oaths, I have ſworn,</hi> ſaith David, <hi>that I will keep thy righteous Judgements;</hi> here were ſtrong purpoſes indeed. And then,</p>
               <p>Seventhly, He that hath this pure heart, certainly hath pure ends in all that he doth, He hath a holy Aim, he hath a ſingle eye, this is a great evidence of a pure heart, when we have pure Aims, Chriſt calls that the ſingle eye, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 23. <hi>If thine eye be ſingle,</hi> that is, If thy ends, and Aims, that which thou lookeſt at, If they are ſingle, ſincere, pure, <hi>the whole body ſhall be full of light.</hi> A pure heart, the ends that he
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60602:42"/> propoſes, are not <hi>ſelf,</hi> not ſelf-profit, not ſelf-applauſe, not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; But he purpoſes the profit of many that they may be ſaved, or the good of all with whom he converſes. He propoſes theſe great ends, which he carries quite through all unto the end. And that is, that he may exalt the name of the Lord by all. O look to your ends, the purity of your hearts, will appear in the purity of your Aims, and of your ends: and ſo much for that firſt thing, for conviction, and diſcovery about this purity of heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe.</hi> 2. Secondly, Let it be a word of exhortation, and that in two branches.</p>
               <p>Firſt, If there be ſuch a thing as a pure heart, and that be of ſuch importance, then weigh it well, whether you have this pure heart, conſider it by all that hath been
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60602:43"/> foreſpoken concerning an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical pure heart, and the evidences thereof; and I would ſay this for the urging of it, that we all ſhould look to this matter, the purity of our hearts.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The hardeſt thing that we have to do, is the purifying of our hearts, and the greateſt kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which God can do us, is to cleanſe our hearts. The cleanſing of the heart is the hardeſt piece of work, it is comparatively an eaſie thing to cleanſe the hand, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively an eaſie thing to cleanſe the <hi>Tongue,</hi> and to have that pure, but to have the heart purified, there's the great ſtick. And then,</p>
               <p>Secondly, Look to the purity of your hearts, for they have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly need of purifying. They whoſe hearts are ſtill in their firſt natural ſtate, they have need indeed, and they who are in a ſpiritual ſtate, have need of daily purifying, look
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60602:43"/> (I ſay) therefore to the purifying of your hearts, for they have need to be purified, they are the filthieſt part of us: If there be impurity in the <hi>hand,</hi> there's much more in the <hi>heart;</hi> and then,</p>
               <p>'Tis indeed a vain thing, to go about to purify the hand, or Tongue, or life, if the heart be Impure. 'Twere a vain thing for any one to go and cleanſe a ſtream, while he know's that there is a Fountain above that ſends forth filthy, and unclean, and poyſonous water. 'Tis juſt ſo in this caſe; till the heart be made pure, nothing can be pure.</p>
               <p>And the great eſteem which God hath of us, is with reſpect to this purity of heart. He is a friend indeed to thoſe who have a pure heart, he hath a great reſpect for them. There is an expreſſion, in <hi>Prov.</hi> 22. 11. <hi>He that loveth pureneſs of heart, for the grace of his lips</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60602:44"/> 
                  <hi>the King ſhall be his friend,</hi> mark there, the <hi>pureneſs of heart,</hi> and <hi>grace of lips.</hi> By grace of lips, he means, not only <hi>graceful</hi> ſpeech, but <hi>gracious</hi> ſpeech. Now grace in the lips you ſee hath its depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the pureneſs of the heart, and ſaith he, he that hath ſuch a pureneſs of heart, as that from it he hath a graceful lip, <hi>the King ſhall be his friend.</hi> Doubtleſs <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſpake this with reference to himſelf, ſhewing what a friend he would be to thoſe that appeared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in pureneſs of heart, and this graciouſneſs of their lips. But this is much more true in reference to the King of Heaven. He that loveth pureneſs of heart, for the grace of of his lips, the King of Heaven ſhall be his friend, he ſhall be accepted of God. And what grace ſoever that is, gracefulneſs of ſpeech any one hath, if there be not pureneſs of heart, he ſhall have no favour with
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60602:44"/> the King of Heaven, what ever he may find among any of the Kings of the Earth. O this therefore is the great thing, <hi>my Son</hi> ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, give me thy heart.</hi> That's it which the Lord doth ſo much delight in, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 26. <hi>My Son, give me thy heart.</hi> What heart muſt it be? Not an unclean heart, not a filthly heart, not a proud heart, not a covetous heart, not a mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious heart, not an uncharitable heart, but <hi>my Son give me thy heart,</hi> give me thy heart purified, purged, cleanſed. Or thus, give me thy heart, reſign it up to me to be purified, to be purged, to be cleanſed, to be made holy. Indeed we may give our proud hearts up to God, and beg of him that he would humble them, But we muſt not think to keep our hearts proud, and give them up to God proud; and we may give our unclean hearts to God, begging of him that he would cleanſe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60602:45"/> them, but we muſt not keep unclean hearts in our boſoms, and then ſay, we give up our hearts to God. The heart in which God is pleaſed, and in with he takes delight, is the pure heart; therefore upon all theſe Conſiderations, let us be much look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the purity of our hearts. And then.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Do you find that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Scripture rule, you have a pure heart, Then I have a ſecond word to ſay. Pray do what you can to keep your hearts pure: For they who have pure hearts may quickly find their hearts very impure, unleſs they look narrowly to it. A heart that is made pure, will be greatly impured unleſs we watch, and keep it pure. <hi>Solomon</hi> hath that expreſſion, in <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 23. <hi>keep thy heart with all diligence,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>For out of it are the Iſſues of life:</hi> keep thy heart, keep it with all diligence, with all manner of keeping; you
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60602:45"/> ſee then, it is not enough to get a pure heart; but we muſt keep our hearts, and keep them clean. As 'tis in this caſe with your houſes, you do not only <hi>make</hi> them clean, but you <hi>keep</hi> them clean: and if a houſe be made never ſo clean, yet it will contract defilement. Duſt will be upon it, unleſs it be kept clean, unleſs it be watcht that none throw dirt into it. Indeed we had need in keeping our hearts, to watch them continually: and that's the great buſineſs of keeping our hearts, for the Devil if we do not watch our hearts, he will do one of theſe two things.</p>
               <p>He will either ſteal away our heart: for the Devil comes a heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtealing continually; and eſpecially when you are at a Sermon, or a holy duty; and if he can but ſteal away your <hi>hearts,</hi> he cares not how many Bodies there are here.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:60602:46"/>
               <p> Or he will be throwing dirt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your hearts, ſuggeſting wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: He will throw dirt into the inner cloſet of your hearts, by his Temptations, by his Injections. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you would keep your hearts clean, you muſt watch them.</p>
               <p>I, and you muſt often waſh your hearts, if you would keep them clean; for your hearts will contract filth, do what you can, unleſs they are daily waſht, and duly ſearcht.</p>
               <p>As it is with a Garden, let a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den be dreſt, and made very exact, ſo that there is not any thing amiſs, not a Weed to be ſeen in it: I, but the Garden muſt be kept thus, or elſe in a little time it will be over-run with Weeds again. It is ſo in our hearts: Suppoſe we have weeded out this, and that, and the other evil, if we do not keep a continual care of our hearts, the Weeds will grow again; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our hearts muſt be continually
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60602:46"/> weeding, and our hearts muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually waſht. We muſt go daily to the <hi>Fountain opened for ſin and for uncleanneſs:</hi> We muſt waſh our hearts by the renewed Acts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, confeſſing our ſins, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing our ſins, mortifying our ſins. This is a great work for us. If you have pure hearts, look to it that you keep them pure; you may quickly be defiled: <hi>David,</hi> a man that had a pure heart; yet got ſo much defilement upon his heart, that he could not tell what to make of it, but begs of God to <hi>create</hi> him a <hi>new heart,</hi> and all becauſe he did not watch his heart, but gave way to Temptation, and ſo was overtaken: then you will find if you do not daily ſweep your houſes, they will defile; and the cob-webs they will grow; the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders will be at work; and though your hearts be never ſo pure, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders will creep into them, this Luſt,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60602:47"/> and that Corruption, and they will be weaving their Webs there. O what ſad Webs we have in the hearts of men, and all becauſe they look not after them! You muſt ſweep down the Cob-webs, and throw out the dirt every day, if you would keep your hearts clean.</p>
               <p>And I would preſs all I have ſaid, by theſe four Conſiderations. Look to it that you have pure hearts, and that you keep your hearts pure.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Upon this Conſideration which you find in Pſal. 18. 26. <hi>With the pure, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf pure: with the merciful, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf merciful:</hi> with an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf upright. <hi>With the pure thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf pure.</hi> I, but if a man be not pure, Will God ſhew himſelf impure towards him? No ſuch thing. Let us be what we will, God is ever the ſame. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60602:47"/> can turn him out of his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. But the meaning is, If we are pure, pure in heart, God will ſhew himſelf pure to us: that is, he will perform all things; he will be that to us which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. He will be all that to us which we can deſire. <hi>With the pure, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf pure.</hi> And he ſaith, <hi>With the froward, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf froward.</hi> As God knows how to deal with men in wayes of evil, to hit them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what they are: With the froward thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf froward. Not that there is any frowardneſs or paſſion in the Lord; but men ſhall be dealt with accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their way. They that will <hi>wreſtle</hi> with God, as the word there ſignifies, he will pay them in their own coin: And ſo with the pure, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf pure. And then,</p>
               <p>Secondly, Look to this purity,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60602:48"/> for then all things are pure to you. As God will ſhew himſelf pure to you: So if you are pure, all things will be pure to you, Titus 1. 15. <hi>Unto the pure, all things are pure; but unto them that are defiled, and unbelieving, is nothing pure.</hi> Here is a very ſtrong Argument to preſs you to this purity of heart: <hi>To the pure, all things are pure.</hi> To the impure, nothing is pure. Why is it that to the pure all things are pure? What are evil actions pure to them? Is ſin pure to them? No: God forbid that any ſhould have ſuch a thought. This liberty have ſome taken to themſelves, as if there were no difference to be made in actions: But, to the pure, all things are pure. They need not trouble themſelves about ſin, or this or that. No, but <hi>to the pure all things are pure:</hi> that is, all things are bleſſed to them: All their enjoyments, all the Ordinances
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60602:48"/> of God, all their outward comforts, all their relations, all their duties, all things are pure to them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, ſaith he, <hi>To them that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, there is nothing pure.</hi> The very holy <hi>Ordinances</hi> are not pure to them: Their <hi>Callings,</hi> though honeſt, are not pure to them: their riches, their great poſſeſſions in the world, are not pure to them: They have not a pure, nor a holy uſe of any of theſe things. This is an awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning conſideration, to look after a pure heart, <hi>To the pure, all things are pure; but to the undefiled there is nothing pure; but even their mind and conſcience is defiled.</hi> And then,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The pure in heart, are only fit for Communion with God, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 22. ſaith he, <hi>With them that call on the Lord, out of a pure heart.</hi> They only are fit to call upon God, who have a pure heart. The Apoſtle would have them lift
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60602:49"/> up <hi>clean hands,</hi> in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8. (much more then, pure hearts, who call upon God <hi>out of a pure heart.)</hi> And when the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> had exhorted them to draw nigh to God, with this Promiſe of Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that he would draw nigh to them, preſently he adds, <hi>Cleanſe your hands ye ſinners, and purifie your hearts ye double minded.</hi> You are no wayes fit for Communion with God, for drawing near to God, unleſs your hearts are thus purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thus purged, thus cleanſed. And then,</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Laſtly, The pure in heart are thoſe that have that great promiſe, the promiſe which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all good; namely, <hi>To ſee God.</hi> Matth. 5. 8. <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart.</hi> Why? Saith he, <hi>They ſhall ſee God.</hi> God is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, God is Inviſible, How ſhall they ſee him? Him no man hath ſeen, nor can ſee. How ſhall the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60602:49"/> pure in heart ſee him? Why, they ſhall ſee him; that is, they ſhall enjoy him, they ſhall have ſweet communion with him; they ſhall aſcend into the Holy Hill, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24. 3, 4. <hi>Who ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend into the Holy Hill? He that hath clean hands, and a pure heart.</hi> They ſhall be admitted nigh to God, they ſhall ſee him, they ſhall enjoy him.</p>
               <p>I may conclude with that of the Prophet, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1. 13. he ſaith, that <hi>God is of purer eyes than to behold iniquity.</hi> And the truth is, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure eyes cannot behold God: They cannot bear the Glory, the Excellency of his preſence: They cannot enjoy God. There is a ſtop in the very nature of the thing, as well as there is a ſtop by a Divine Law. Thus the Impoſture ſhall not come into the preſence of God; that's the Divine Law. And there is a ſtop in the very nature of the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60602:50"/> thing: they cannot abide in the preſence of God. As he is of purer eyes, than to behold evil: ſo evil ones have ſuch impure eyes, that they cannot behold him, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee God.</p>
               <p>Now then, let this be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and lay it to heart, what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you have to look after this <hi>pure heart,</hi> which is the firſt of thoſe three ſprings, out of which ſaith the Apoſtle, all thoſe holy actions, which are the end, and the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Commandment of God muſt flow, and with which only it is that you may come to have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance. And ſo much now of the firſt of the Springs, The Pure Heart. The ſecond is, a Good Conſcience.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:60602:50"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 92. 12.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>The righteous ſhall flouriſh like the Palm-tree. He ſhall grow like a Cedar in</hi> Lebanon.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>VVE ſee commonly that oppoſites, either per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or things, being laid together, illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and ſet off one another. (To touch at no other things in this Pſalm) Here are two of the greateſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites in this world laid together, and they do wonderfully illuſtrate each other.</p>
            <p>The oppoſites are, the <hi>Wicked</hi> and the <hi>Righteous.</hi> And indeed, thoſe two divide the whole world.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:60602:51"/>
            <p> The ſtate of the wicked, is ſet down at the ſeventh Verſe, <hi>They may ſpring as the Graſs, they may flouriſh.</hi> But what's the iſſue of it? <hi>It is that they ſhall be deſtroyed for ever.</hi> They ſhall <hi>ſpring,</hi> but they ſhall ſpring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but <hi>like Graſs,</hi> which is Green for a while, and quickly wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Righteous</hi> at this twelfth Verſe, (For I ſhall not enlarge fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the ſtate of the wicked; but only to ſet off the ſtate of the Righteous.) The Righteous ſhall flouriſh too. But how? Not like the <hi>Graſs,</hi> but like the <hi>Palm-tree.</hi> And indeed, they ſhall <hi>abide for ever:</hi> whereas the wicked, they ſhall be <hi>deſtroyed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who the <hi>Righteous</hi> are, I ſhall not ſtay to ſpeak of at large.</p>
            <p>They are ſuch as are righteous in their ſtate, being in the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And they are ſuch as are righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in their courſe, and in their
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60602:51"/> life, walking anſwerably to ſuch a ſtate.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Righteous</hi> ones ſhall <hi>flouriſh.</hi> They ſhall not only <hi>Live</hi> and <hi>Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,</hi> but they ſhall have a flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, Mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies <hi>live,</hi> and are <hi>mighty.</hi> 'Tis true, they do ſo for a time, many times. The Righteous live, and they have a mightineſs too. <hi>For they flouriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how do they flouriſh? Not as the Graſs, but as the <hi>Palm-tree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall only open that a little, and touch only upon one point, from the Paralel. <hi>They ſhall flouriſh as the Palm-tree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Palm-tree is an excellent tree, and the praiſes of God are often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled by it: Nay, they are ſaid in the <hi>Revelation</hi> to have Palms in their hands. And they are ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Palm-tree, in the Prophecy of <hi>Ezekiel, Chap.</hi> 40. 31. in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when it is ſaid, They ſhall
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60602:52"/> 
               <hi>flouriſh like a Palm-tree:</hi> We muſt conſider how the Palm-tree flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes.</p>
            <p>The Palm tree, (only to touch that) is the <hi>Date-tree,</hi> that's the Palm-tree. And ſo the Meeter, or Singing Pſalms expreſſes it. There it is rendred thus,</p>
            <q>
               <l>The Juſt ſhall flouriſh up on high,</l>
               <l>As Date-trees bud and blow.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now there are five things which are obſerved in the Date-tree, I ſhall name them all, but ſpeak only a little to one to carry on this point of the flouriſhing of the Righteous like the Palm-tree.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Date, or the Palm-tree grows in the pureſt ſoil: it will not grow in filthy places, in dungy places, but it loves a very pure ſoil. And thus the Righteous flouriſh: They flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in a very pure ſoil: for they are planted in that which is the pureſt ſoil of all: They are planted in
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60602:52"/> Chriſt: They grow in Chriſt; and they grow in the Church, which is a pure ſoil. They are planted in the houſe of God, as it follows in the <hi>Pſalm.</hi> Not in the world, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean and polluted world, which lyes in wickedneſs, and ſmells like a dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, but in the Garden of God. And,</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Palm-tree is a Tree whoſe branches do ſhoot all upwards: there's none grow out of the ſide, as other Trees have. And thus the Righteous flouriſh as the Palm-tree: their affections are ſet upon things above: they grow up Heaven-ward. They do not ſhoot out their branches this way, or that way to the world, but all to Heaven. So it is while they act according to their ſtate.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Palm-trees are thoſe Trees which are alwayes green: Green in Winter as well as in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. It doth not caſt its leaf, nor fade; as the expreſſion is in <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:60602:53"/> 1. 3. The godly man is like a Tree planted by the Rivers of Water, that bringeth forth his fruit in his ſeaſon, <hi>His leaf alſo ſhall not wither.</hi> They hold up their profeſſion: they are green, not only in the Summer of proſperity, but in the very Winter of adverſity; and maintain their verdure, and their beauty in the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt times.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Palm-tree is a Tree that doth not only keep its greenneſs, the beauty of its <hi>leaves;</hi> but it is a Tree that is full of fruit; and that <hi>good fruit,</hi> pleaſant fruit, ſweet fruit. a kind of Cordial fruit, which you know the Date is. The Righteous have the greenneſs of a profeſſion: and beſides that, they have the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of their Converſation; and 'tis pleaſant fruit, fruits of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, fruits of Faith, fruits of Love, the fruits of the Spirit. They are fruitful Trees, ſuch a one as the Palm.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, (Which I ſhall a little
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60602:53"/> inſiſt upon.) They flouriſh like the Palm-tree. It is ſo far noted, that it is made an Emblem. The Palm-tree doth grow up, when it is moſt preſt down. When there are the heavieſt weights hung upon the Palm-tree, then the Palm-tree riſes up higheſt. It grows higheſt, when it is (as it were) kept down. Thus it is with the Righteous; they flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh like the Palm-tree: And that's the Note that I ſhall give you, and ſpeak a little to.</p>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>DOCT. That Righteous perſons, ſuch as are righteous in their ſtate, in a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified ſtate; and Righteous in their courſe, walking in holineſs, they do improve and grow under great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt preſſures. When they meet with the greateſt preſſures in the world, they thrive and grow Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ward.</head>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60602:54"/>
               <p> This only I ſhall ſpeak a little to. When the world would cruſh the Righteous, preſs them down to the earth, yea, preſs them down to <hi>Hell</hi> if they could, yet like the Palm-teee, they grow up more and more.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who were the Church of God in <hi>Exod.</hi> 1. that when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> put weights upon them, the weights of very heavy oppreſſion; when he ſet over them Task-maſters to afflict them with their burthens at <hi>ver.</hi> 11. it is ſaid ver. 12. <hi>But the more they afflicted them, the more they multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed and grew.</hi> This was juſt like the Palm-tree. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> burthened them, but they multiplyed and grew. And ſurely we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this, not only of their multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying in <hi>number,</hi> but of their mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying in <hi>goodneſs</hi> too, or their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in goodneſs: they multiplyed and grew (Doubtleſs there is that ſenſe in it) not only that they had a greater company, and more fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60602:54"/> as to the production of perſons, but that they were more fruitful in their lives. And that's it which hath been ſaid of the Church at all times, when under preſſures and burthens. Saith One, They were bound, they were beaten, they were burnt, and yet they multiplyed and increaſed. And doubtleſs, it was with the two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold increaſe I ſpake of before. The more perſons were added to the Church; and thoſe perſons that were added, advanced more in wayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Grace, in wayes of Holineſs. And ſo that other ſaying of the Antients upon this very point; <hi>That the blood of the Martyrs was the ſeed of the Church.</hi> It was like ſeed indeed, and it brought forth, as the ſeed ſpoken of in <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. The good ſeed falling upon good ground, brought forth, in ſome thirty, in ſome ſixty, in ſome an hundred fold. This is flouriſhing like the Palm-tree. And that we find in Dan. 11. 35. <hi>And ſome of them of</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:60602:55"/> 
                  <hi>underſtanding ſhall fall.</hi> Shall fall! How? Shall fall into the hand, and under the hands of perſecuting Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants; they ſhall fall into trouble; like that in the <hi>Proverbs, The Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous falleth ſeven times a day.</hi> That is, he falls often into trouble, yet God helps them up again. Now ſaith he, ſome of them of <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding;</hi> that is, of a ſpiritual un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, of a holy underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: they ſhall fall into afflictions: for them of underſtanding, we may explain it by Dan. 12. 10. <hi>None of the wicked ſhall underſtand, but the wiſe ſhall underſtand.</hi> The godly wiſe, they ſhall underſtand. Now of theſe men of underſtanding: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall fall: Well, what ſhall be the effect of it? <hi>To try them.</hi> That's the Firſt.</p>
               <p>And not only ſo, but to purge, and to make them white. To purge out their corruptions, and to make their Graces very conſpicuous. You ſee the improvement they made of their
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60602:55"/> afflictions and ſufferings for the truths of God: and that in Zach. 13. 9. teaches the ſame thing. <hi>I will bring the third part through the fire:</hi> through the fire of perſecution. And what, ſhall they be burnt there? No, ſaith he, <hi>I will refine them as Silver is refined, and will try them as Gold is tryed: and they ſhall call on my Name, and I will hear them, I will ſay, it is my people; and they ſhall ſay, The Lord is my God.</hi> Thus they ſhall grow up in the actings of their faith to an aſſurance. Faith ſhall come to an appropriating act; they ſhall ſay, <hi>The Lord is my God.</hi> And when? Even when I bring them through the fire. I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine them ſo, that their faith ſhall be exceeding tranſparent: and they ſhall ſay, <hi>The Lord is my God.</hi> And we know what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> found by the ſufferings which befell him; and in him the Church of God, Phil. 1. 12. ſaith he, <hi>I would you ſhould underſtand, Brethren, that the thing</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:60602:56"/> 
                  <hi>which happened unto me—</hi>Why, what things were theſe that hapned to <hi>Paul?</hi> What was it ſome great preferment, (as we ſay) ſome great Benefice, ſome great honour? No, the things that befell him, were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and afflictions; <hi>Bonds,</hi> as he doth expreſs it in <hi>ver.</hi> 13. Now ſaith he, Theſe have <hi>fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the Goſpel.</hi> How, to the furtherance of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel? Why, becauſe perſons by this affliction upon me, which threatned them alſo; and 'tis like took hold of ſome of them: why, ſaith he, <hi>They waxed confident by my bonds, and are much more bold to ſpeak the Word without fear,</hi> ver. 14. They grew up like the Palm tree; they grew to a confidence. They were not only <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>faithful,</hi> but they were <hi>confident</hi> and <hi>bold.</hi> They had not only integrity for Chriſt, but a great increaſe of ſtrength for Chriſt; and all upon his ſufferings: They flouriſh like the Palm-tree.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60602:56"/> And that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. will reach it too: ſaith he, <hi>We glory in tribulation, knowing that tribulation worketh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and patience experience, and experience hope.</hi> Why, tribulation did not hinder their Graces, but did further them. Tribulation did work patience. It ſeem's to be a very ſtrange ſting. Tribulation doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe patience indeed: But how? It did work patience, or make them more patient: for that's the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. Now it ſeems very ſtrange, yet thus it doth. And then Patience experience, and experience hope. Here's a flouriſhing, and a growing up in all Graces, even in a time of tribulation. And it's the ſame thing that we have too in 2 Cor. 4. 17. <hi>Our light affliction which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory.</hi> That is, it works us into a greater fitneſs for glory, the afflictions that are upon us. We grow more up into Heaven,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60602:57"/> more into glory. Our hope doth (as it were) riſe up into glory by our affliction: And this is flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like the Palm-tree. Affliction will make us the fitter for Heaven: they will make us better than we were, and ſo fitter for Heaven, fitter for glory. Grace improved is very near to glory. Thus we ſee how the Scripture holds out this thing, that the righteous flouriſh as the Palm-tree. They are bettered, and made fitter by their afflictions for glory.</p>
               <p>I will give you an account in ſome grounds of it, why it is ſo, how it comes to paſs.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The preſſures and weights that are upon the Righteous from the world, do wean them from the world, takes them off from the world. Why now the love of the world, and cleaving to the world, and deſires going after the world, are a mighty impediment to our growth in grace, to our <hi>flouriſhing</hi> in the world. You ſee what's ſaid in <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60602:57"/> cares of the world, the pleaſures of the world, the deceitfulneſs of riches, choke the Word, and make it become altogether unfruitful. And truly the love of the world, and purſuit of worldly things, do exceedingly hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grace in the fourth Ground, in thoſe that are truly godly, it is a great hindrance to them till they get their hearts mortified to the world, and weaned from the world. Now certainly the preſſures that we meet withal in the world, are an exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great means to take us off from the pleaſures of the world, and the profits of the world. We are morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the world: as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the Croſs of Chriſt, Gal. 6. 14. <hi>God forbid that I ſhould glory in any thing ſave in the Croſs of Chriſt.</hi> What's the Croſs of Chriſt? Why, the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings which I have for Chriſt, the weights which are laid upon me for Chriſts ſake. What was the effect of this? Why, <hi>whereby I am cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied unto the world, and the world un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:60602:58"/> 
                  <hi>me.</hi> Now when the ſoul is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from this world, this evil world, it muſt needs flouriſh up to the other world.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By the afflictions and troubles we meet with in this world, we get much light, and grow into a clearer knowledge of thoſe things which makes for our increaſes Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-ward. It hath been antiently ſaid, That affliction gives under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and the School of the Croſs, is the School of light. Light comes in while we are in the School of the Croſs. And indeed there is a fourfold light doth come in to us while we are under the Croſs, and under ſufferings. A light,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Which diſcovers more to us the vanity of the world, than ever we ſaw before, and the baſeneſs of the world, and the wickedneſs of the world: and this is a great advantage to us. And,</p>
               <p>Secondly, A light to ſee more of of the Mind of God, and of the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60602:58"/> Word of God. So <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Pſal</hi> 119. 71. <hi>It was good for me that I have been afflicted, for thereby I have learned thy Statutes.</hi> Saith he, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them? I have more of thy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and I have learned every Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute more. There hath come in a clearer light into my ſoul now by my afflictions. A ſtate of affliction is in it ſelf called in Scripture, <hi>A ſtate of Darkneſs:</hi> it is a time of darkneſs: and yet it is wonderful, that out of this Darkneſs there comes a light; a ſpiritual light: ſo that we ſee more of the Word of God, and of the wonderful things of the Law.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It muſt needs follow, that by affliction we have a clearer light to ſee the worth of grace, and of an intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, what an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent thing that is. And then,</p>
               <p>Fourthly, A clearer light to ſee the excellency of Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. As of an <hi>Intereſt</hi> in Chriſt, ſo of the <hi>perſon</hi> of Chriſt, how glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60602:59"/> how choice a one Jeſus Chriſt is. I do but touch this now: By affliction a light comes into the ſoul: Upon all theſe, or upon other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, we muſt needs improve Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-ward, and grow up like the Palm-tree. In 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18. ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Grow in Grace.</hi> Why how ſhould we come to grow in grace? Why ſaith he, <hi>And in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> In proportion to our growth in the knowledge, in the true knowledge; I ſpeak not of a notional knowledge, a meer brain knowledge, but of an experimental knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt. As we increaſe in this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſo we increaſe and grow in grace: and ſo of the reſt. As we grow in the knowledge of the vanity of the world: as we grow in the knowledge of the Word of God; as we grow in the knowledge of the worth of grace, and of an intereſt in Chriſt; as we grow in the knowledge of the excellency of the knowledge of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60602:59"/> the Perſon of Chriſt, ſo we muſt needs grow in grace. Now then, the Croſs and affliction giving us an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage for all theſe things, you ſee the ground of it. And then,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The weights and preſſures which are upon theſe Palm-trees, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Righteous, they do draw them more into their own hearts, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe more at home, to ſearch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more, to be acquainted more with their own boſomes, and this will make us flouriſh, and grow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: for indeed the reaſon why we grow up ſo little in acquaintance with Chriſt, lyes much in this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we grow ſo little in acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with our ſelves. Now in an afflicted condition (if ever) the ſoul is upon its return to it ſelf. In <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. when the whole Church was in that ſad condition, under thoſe grievous weights of Captivity, and all manner of trouble they were in: ſay they, <hi>Let us ſearch and try our ſelves.</hi> Come, now let's go in to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60602:60"/> our ſelves; let us ſearch for our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions; ſearch for our luſts, which lye in the ſecret corners of our hearts; let us ſearch our ſelves, and let us ſearch how it is with us as to Grace; what faith we have, what love we have, what patience, and ſo of the reſt. Indeed, afflictions do put us upon this ſearch of our ſelves, to find out the ſtate of our graces; how it is with us, what condition they are in, how they fare. Now this the troubles we meet with in the world, give us an advantage for, and ſo an advantage of ſpiritual growth, of growing Heaven-ward, as the Palm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree. And then,</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Theſe afflictions and preſſures we have from the world, drive us nearer to God. As to a more acquaintance with our ſelves, ſo to a more acquaintance with God, and more communion with Chriſt. They do (as it were) force us to Chriſt, when the world deals ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly with us. Many times when
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60602:60"/> the world is kind to us, ſail with us, and flatters us, and huggs us, and embraces us, we begin to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, and to ſlight communion with Jeſus Chriſt; and to ſay as they in Jer. 2. <hi>We are Lords, we will come no more at thee.</hi> It is ſpoken of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they were in a very flouriſhing condition. I, but when they were ſlaves, and in cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, and in a ſad condition, truly then they ſaw reaſon to come to Chriſt, to come to him by prayer. The very Mariners in <hi>Jonah,</hi> when they were in the ſtorm, every one went to his God. Iſa. 26. <hi>In their trouble they have viſited me.</hi> To be ſure I ſhall hear of them then, <hi>In their affliction they will ſeek me early.</hi> It is ſo in evil men, much more is it ſo in the righteous, and in thoſe that have walkt with God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If they have had a conſtant communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God and Jeſus Chriſt in a time of peace and proſperity, ſurely in a time of preſſures they have
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60602:61"/> much more communion with him. Now this muſt needs cauſe the ſoul to increaſe and flouriſh. For the nearer we are to God, the more we have of God, and receive impreſſions from him; as <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he was with God in the Mount, his face did ſhine. But in times of outward peace, and when all is well, O we are very ready to neglect communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Laſtly, While the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are under weights and preſtures, like a Palm-tree, they have a ſpecial promiſe of the preſence of God with them; and this is that which makes them flouriſh indeed. It is not our being in affliction, which will make us better, and make us grow Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-ward; but it is Chriſt being with us in affliction. It is Gods ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting himſelf to us in affliction which makes us grow, and flouriſh like a Palm-tree. Now I need not ſtay to tell you how many promiſes there are of the ſpecial preſence of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60602:61"/> God to his people while they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Croſs, that in Iſa. 43. 2. <hi>When thou paſſeſt through the waters, I will be with thee; and through the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee; when thou walkeſt through the fire thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi> I will be with thee. And truly the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God with us, it is not only for this end (Though that be there expreſt) that we ſhall not be quite ſwallowed up, that the water ſhall not drown us, nor the fire conſume us; but that the fire and water ſhall not conſume us as to our ſoul ſtate. That we ſhall not ſuffer loſs or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment in our ſpiritual ſtate, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the fire or water; but that we ſhall increaſe there, and grow there. So in 1 Pet. 4. 14. <hi>If ye be reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Name of Chriſt, happy are ye; for the Spirit of Glory and of God reſteth on you.</hi> It doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>come</hi> to you, and <hi>viſit</hi> you, but it <hi>reſts</hi> upon you. Now when the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60602:62"/> Spirit of God is, eſpecially when the Spirit of God <hi>reſts,</hi> and doth abide, there muſt needs be a growth, and an increaſe in our ſpiritual ſtate. But ſo it is, while we are under theſe afflicting diſpenſations, when the weights are upon us, we have promiſes of more of the preſence of God, and of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Spirit, and of the reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Spirit; and therefore we ſhall flouriſh, flouriſh ſpiritually, flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in our inner man: That may ſerve for the clearing of the Point, That the <hi>Righteous flouriſh as the Palm-tree, under weights and preſſures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Application.</hi> Firſt, This may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm us in a twofold Scripture-truth.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That there is no wiſdom, nor counſel againſt the Lord. That's a Scripture aſſertion, which receives a mighty confirmation by this point. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21. 30. This point doth migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily confirm it. Why, what's the Counſel, what's the purpoſe of the world, when they hang their weights upon the Palm-trees, upon the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60602:62"/> what's the meaning? You ſhall underſtand their meaning: when the firſt weights that we read of in the Scripture were ever hung upon theſe Palm-trees, in the place before quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Exod. 1. 10. <hi>Come on,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Let us deal wiſely with them.</hi> The Wiſe man ſaith in the <hi>Proverbs, There is no wiſdom, nor counſel againſt the Lord.</hi> Well, ſaith he here, <hi>Let us deal wiſely with them.</hi> To what purpoſe? Why, ſaith he, <hi>Leſt they multiply.</hi> We will keep them down; keep them down, that their perſons multiply not; and we will keep them down too, that their Graces multiply not. Truly this is the deſign of the Counſels of men, in hanging their weights upon the Palm-trees; and ſo it hath been all along in the ſufferings of the Church. What hath been their wiſdoms? They thought by their ſufferings to keep down thoſe truths which they profeſt, which it may be they call'd <hi>Hereſie:</hi> As <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>After the</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60602:63"/> 
                  <hi>way which you call Hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers.</hi> Hereſies, they thought to ſuppreſs them as Errors and Hereſies.</p>
               <p>And they thought again to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the profeſſors: yea, they thought not only to diſcourage them in matters of truth, of faith and worſhip; but they thought to turn them quite aſide; to make them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it, to forſake it, to apoſtatize, to backſlide, to deny the faith. This is the thing which they have had in their eye, in all the preſſures which they have laid upon the people of God from one time to another, to ſtrip them of their faith, and to ſtrip them of the truth; to break them in the things of God. Now I ſay, this is their Counſel. And mark what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>There is no wiſdom, nor counſel againſt the Lord.</hi> They thought to hinder them in all theſe things, to ſuppreſs the truth, to diſcourage the profeſſors of the truth, and to cauſe them to turn
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60602:63"/> away, and to deny the truth. But they have fail'd in it: for they mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed; and the truth multiplyed; and they flouriſht more by the weights and burdens that were upon their backs. So that we may ſay in this caſe, as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 44. 25. <hi>That the Lord turns the Counſels of the wicked hackward.</hi> Turneth wiſe men backward: that is, their wiſdom which they have been exerciſing, that hath produced a quite contrary effect to what they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: they thought to hinder the truth; and they have been rather a furtherance to it, as <hi>Pauls</hi> word is in the firſt of the <hi>Philippians.</hi> Theſe things have hapned to the furtherance of the Goſpel, which they thought ſhould have ruined the Goſpel. And this indeed is ſo notorious, that the enemies of the Goſpel have been forced many times to acknowledge, and to confeſs it with grief, That the righteous have flouriſht like Palm-trees. In <hi>Exod.</hi> 1. 12. when it
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60602:64"/> is ſaid, the <hi>more they afflicted them, the more they multiplyed and grew.</hi> And what follows? <hi>And they,</hi> that is, the <hi>Aegyptians, were grieved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the children of Iſrael.</hi> We ſee we cannot bring them down: their Counſels went quite backward. And you have the like in <hi>John</hi> 12. 19. The Phariſees when they had done all that they could to hinder the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples receiving of Jeſus Chriſt, they ſaid among themſelves, <hi>Perceive ye how ye prevail nothing? Behold, the world is gone after him.</hi> You ſee they were fain to make an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of this thing their own ſelves. We have been labouring to ſtop the progreſs of this man, but we find it quite otherwiſe; we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail nothing at all. Not only, not <hi>much,</hi> but <hi>nothing. And behold, the world is gone after him.</hi> He will get all the world ſhortly, they multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſo faſt. So that we ſee from this, the truth of the Scripture, that there is no Counſel againſt the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:60602:64"/>
               <p> And it may give you a further confirmation by way of Inſtruction, concerning that great truth, in Rom. 8. 28. <hi>All things ſhall work together for good to them that ſerve God, and are the called according to his purpoſe. All things work together for good.</hi> What things? Troubles, afflictions, preſſures, burdens which are laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, they work for good. Why, this is one of the greateſt goods that can be, to have grace flouriſh and grow. Faith and Humility, and Love to Jeſus Chriſt, if one increaſe in theſe things. What is worthy the name of <hi>good,</hi> in compariſon of an increaſe of theſe things. That's one thing we may take notice of from it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We ſhould be hence raiſed up in our hearts, to magnifie the power, wiſdom and goodneſs of God, who doth thus over-rule theſe things for his people: for certainly this doth declare the wonderful work of God. In <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. where he hath a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60602:65"/> notable Allegory, and ſpeaks of the troubles and ſufferings of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people of God: For all that that is ſpoken of the <hi>Plowman,</hi> and of the <hi>Threſher,</hi> and of the <hi>bruiſing of the Corn</hi> with threſhing Inſtruments, they do reſpect affliction and troubles which come upon the people of God, (as is clear.) But now, ſaith he, in the cloſe of that Chapter, <hi>This alſo cometh from the Lord of Hoſts, which is wonderful in counſel, and excellent in working.</hi> We may wonder at the counſel and wiſdom of God, who doth his people good by <hi>threſhing them,</hi> and <hi>bringing the wheel over them.</hi> Here are ſeveral ſorts of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and ſufferings, ſome leſſer, and ſome greater. Now all this is but to ſeparate the good ſeed from the chaff, and to make it more fit for uſe: for while the Corn is in the ear, it is not fit for uſe, and we cannot make bread of it untill it be threſht. Now the Lord hath ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wayes to do it. But ſaith he,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60602:65"/> 
                  <hi>This cometh forth from the Lord of Hoſts, which is wonderful in counſel, and excellent in working.</hi> Truly we may ſay, How wonderful is the counſel of the Lord! How excellent is his working, that he makes the Righteous to flouriſh like the Palm-tree; to grow upwards, by that which one would think ſhould bring them down! As when we ſee the Corn laid at, and threſht with a Flail, one would think there were great hurt intended to the Corn; but it is only to ſeparate it from the chaff, that it may appear in its own beauty and uſefulneſs. So the Lord hath a flail of tribulation, to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Chaff from the Wheat. Thoſe acts of Providence towards Gods people, which ſeem to be for their hurt and undoing, when they are threſht as it were by the world, it is only to make them appear what they are. That which we find in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. 22. concerning the wicked, by that we may obſerve the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60602:66"/> difference, and dealings of God with the wicked, who flouriſh as the Graſs, and the righteous. <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks there of ſuch, and ſaith he, <hi>Let their table become a ſnare, and that which ſhould have been for their welfare, let it become a trap:</hi> that is, the Lord doth curſe their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts. By <hi>Table,</hi> he means the good things upon their table: when they have a full table, a plentiful table. And ſo all outward proſperity, ſaith he, it ſhall be a <hi>ſnare</hi> to them. <hi>And that which ſhould have been for their good:</hi> that is, that which in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it is for their good, <hi>It ſhall be an occaſion for their falling:</hi> they ſhall grow more hardned by it, more proud by it, and more impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent by it, and more ſtrangers to God by it. But now when the Lord ſpeaks of a righteous man, here the thing which was appointed for his <hi>ſnare,</hi> as the troubles and perſecutions which lye upon him in the world, ſhall be a table to him; his very
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60602:66"/> ſnares ſhall be a table to his Inner man, where his Graces ſhall come and feed, and grow fat, and flouriſh, and increaſe. The things which the men of the world have deviſed for his falling, they ſhall be to him an occaſion of good. This is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and we are to bleſs the Lord for it, when we find ſuch effects of it: when we ſee it ſo in others, or have any experience of it in our ſelves, that our afflictions do not ſnare us, but are a table to our Graces. That's another thing, to give God the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it; for it is not in the nature of theſe things to do it. No, things would work quite otherwiſe, but that God is wonderful in his Counſels, and excellent in his workings towards his people: they would rather drive us from God, and deſtroy our graces.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Seeing it is ſo, that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ones do flouriſh as the Palm-tree, then when any weights of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60602:67"/> either perſonal or publick, or perſecution, or whatſoever are upon any of us, let us mind the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God towards us. Let us not think that he comes to hurt us, but to make us grow and flouriſh like a Palm-tree. Let us mind this, and joyn with God in this Counſel, in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch things upon his people: Let us joyn with God, and promote the Counſel of God in our own hearts and lives, and in the hearts and lives of others, that they may be bettered by their ſufferings, and be encouraged by their ſufferings, to believe more in God, and more for God, than ever they were. God doth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend us hurt, but good by it; and ſo we ſhould find it, if we were wiſe to joyn with him in his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, And then I would ſay yet further, This may be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Tryal to us. We may take a tryal of our ſelves, both as to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60602:67"/> the ſtate of our perſons, and as to the ſtate of our graces.</p>
               <p>Firſt, As to the ſtate of our perſons: Why, how is it with us under ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings? Do we improve by them? Do we grow, do we flouriſh, though we have theſe weights upon us? Why, truly it is an argument and evidence that our ſtate is good: for a bad man is not made the better by the evils that are upon him. I know God may uſe afflictions to change a man; but unſound hearts, they that have been unſound and falſe in the profeſſion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, they do diſcover themſelves in ſuch a time, ſhew their rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and their naughtineſs. And it is a very great queſtion, whether they that are not bettered by affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, were ever good. Though I would not ſpeak it to lay a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon any. Our betterings ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times under afflictions, is not very dicernable, at leaſt at preſent. But
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60602:68"/> I ſay, it may put us much upon a doubt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whether we, or any were ever really good, if we are not bettered by afflictions, and by try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and by the troubles that are upon us, and by our fears, and by our dangers.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe, we may hence have a great tryal, as to the ſtate of our graces, whether our graces are in good plight, yea, or no. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if faith be down (and the like) we ſhall make little improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all our afflictions and croſſes. If love to Chriſt be down, we ſhall rather be upon the loſing ſide. But now if we find that we are increaſed, and are growing and flouriſhing in ſpirituals, when the weight and preſſure is upon us, it is an argument that our graces are in a good ſtate: and grace is in a good ſtate when it thrives, and thrives by ſuch means, as ſeem ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the quenching of grace,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60602:68"/> and the hinderance of grace; and therefore truly we ſhould conſider our ſelves at this day: for certainly the Palm-trees are now with their weights upon them, and many have diſcovered themſelves ſadly as to their perſons, ſtates, and the ſtate of their graces, that they have very little love to, and faith in Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe they have not flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht in ſuch a day; but rather have declined, and withdrawn, and been aſhamed of what they have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been. And therefore let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that which the Apoſtle ſpeaks in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. ſpeaking of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, which are ſufferings for Chriſt, (that's taken in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) not only thoſe afflictions, which are fatherly chaſtiſements from the hand of God; but thoſe which are from men, for righteouſneſs ſake. Certainly that is the purpoſe of God; it is all for our profit. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us conſider, whether we
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60602:69"/> profit, yea, or no. <hi>We have had Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our fleſh which corrected us; and we gave them reverence: Shall we not much rather be in ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Father of Spirits, and live?</hi> Submit to the will of God, if he will lay any tribulation upon us for his Name ſake; for he hath done all for our profit. What profit? For the profit of our purſes, and eſtates in this world? No, for a better profit than all that; for our profit, that we might be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his holineſs.</p>
               <p>And truly that is another thing, with which I ſhall conclude. We ſay this, That we have no reaſon to be impatient under afflictions and perſecutions, under the troubles we meet with in this world for the Name of Chriſt. Why? for they are for our profit, for our grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and that we may be made more partakers of the holineſs of God: That we may be better
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60602:69"/> while we live, and fitter to dye, and to glorifie him both living and dying.</p>
               <p>And thus I have only toucht theſe things, <hi>That the Righteous do flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh like the Palm-tree, with their weights and preſſures upon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:60602:70"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:60602:70"/>
            <head>Books Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>John Hancok, Senior</hi> and <hi>Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or,</hi> at the firſt Shop in <hi>Popes-Head-Alley,</hi> at the Three Bibles; Who ſells all ſorts of Divinity-Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to Chapmen, or others.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>TWelve Books lately publiſhed by Mr.</hi> Thomas Brooks, <hi>late Preacher of the Goſpel at</hi> Margarets New-Fiſh-ſtreet.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Precious Remedies</hi> againſt Satans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices; <hi>Or,</hi> Salve for Believers and Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers ſores; being a companion for thoſe that are in Chriſt, or out of Chriſt, that ſlight or neglect Ordinances, under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of living above them; that are growing in Spirituals, or decaying; that are tempted, or deſerted; afflicted, or oppoſed; that have aſſurance, or want it; on 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 11.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:60602:71"/> 2. <hi>Heaven on Earth;</hi> Or, a ſerious Diſcourſe touching a well-grounded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of mans everlaſting happineſs and bleſſedneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſearchable Riches of Chriſt:</hi> Or Meat for ſtrong Men, and Milk for Babes, held forth in two and twenty Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, from <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 8. Preached on his Lecture-nights at <hi>Fiſh-ſtreet-hill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>His Apples of Gold for young Men and Women; &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the Young Mans Objections an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, and the Old Mans Doubts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>A String of Pearls:</hi> Or, The beſt things reſerved till laſt; delivered in a Sermon preached in <hi>London, June</hi> 8. 1657. at the Funeral of that Triumphant Saint Mrs. <hi>Mary Blake,</hi> late Wife to his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Friend Mr. <hi>Nicholas Blake,</hi> Merchant.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The Mute Chriſtian; with Soveraign Antidotes againſt the moſt miſerable Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents:</hi> Or, a Chriſtian with an Olive-leaf in his mouth, when he is under the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt afflictions, the ſharpeſt and ſoreſt try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and troubles, the ſaddeſt and darkeſt Providences and Changes.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>An Ark for all Gods</hi> Noahs <hi>in a ſtormy day.</hi> Wherein is ſhewed the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent
<pb facs="tcp:60602:71"/> excellency of a Believers porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; on <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 24.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>The Crown and Glory of Chriſtianity:</hi> Or, Holineſs the only way to happineſs diſcovered in 48 Sermons on <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 14.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>The Privy Key of Heaven;</hi> Or, a Diſcourſe of Cloſet-Prayer, twenty Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for it, with the Reſolution of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral conſiderable Queſtions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>A Heavenly Cordial for all that have had, or have eſcaped the Plague,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="11">11. There is now publiſhed an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent new Book of Mr. <hi>Brooks,</hi> Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>A Cabinet of Choice Jewels,</hi> or a <hi>Box of Precious Oyntment,</hi> Containing eighteen ſpecial Maxims, Conſiderations, Rules and Directions, that are ſeriouſly to be minded and obſerved in order to the clearing up a mans intereſt in Chriſt, the ſaving-work of God upon his own ſoul, and his Title to all the glory of another world.</p>
            <p>Alſo declaring ſeveral Evidences and Marks of True ſaving Grace.</p>
            <p n="12">12. There is now printed <hi>Londons La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations:</hi> Or, a ſober ſerious diſcourſe concerning the late fiery diſpenſation, wherein the procuring cauſes, and the final cauſes of that dreadful diſpenſation
<pb facs="tcp:60602:72"/> are laid open, both upon thoſe who hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been burnt up, and upon thoſe who have eſcaped thoſe conſuming Flames.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bridges Remains:</hi> being eight Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <hi>viz.</hi> Of Mans Bleſſedneſs: 2. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections Rightly placed. 3. How to walk with God in our Calling. 4. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Good and Bad Company. 5. The Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nality of Profeſſors. 6. What our Work is and how to be done. 7. Soul Reſignati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on into the hands of God. 8. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dignity and Duty of Gods Called Ones Which was the laſt that ever wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preacht by that Learned and Judiciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Divine Mr. <hi>William Bridge,</hi> late Preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Word of God at <hi>Yarmouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Diſcourſe of Chriſts coming:</hi> And the Influence, which the Expectation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath on all manner of holy Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and Godlineſs. By <hi>Theophilus Gale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are ſome other Pieces of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Author of theſe Sermons preparing for the Preſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60602:72"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
